<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fruits of unrighteousnes and injustice Brought forth by John Bulkley, and Thomas Bowrman, and the rest of the rulers in Hampshire, against the innocent people of God called Quakers. Who in words and writings have often declared their unjust sufferings; as also at two sessions, and two general assizes holden at Winchester, requiring justice and equity, and their right and liberty in the nation; of the which being still most unjustly deprived, it is now publiquely declared, that they and others seeing their deeds of darknesse brought to light, may be warned, and learn to do justice, and to relieve the oppressed. Also the sounding voyce of the dread of Gods mighty power to all the judges and rulers of the earth, who rise up aginst the Lamb, and to all the host of powers of darknesse who fight against God. By the servants of Christ ... called Humphry Smith. Anthony Melledg. George Henderson. James Potter. Will: Baily. Daniel Baker. John Day. Winifred Newman.</title>
            <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216933</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828646</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1858:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fruits of unrighteousnes and injustice Brought forth by John Bulkley, and Thomas Bowrman, and the rest of the rulers in Hampshire, against the innocent people of God called Quakers. Who in words and writings have often declared their unjust sufferings; as also at two sessions, and two general assizes holden at Winchester, requiring justice and equity, and their right and liberty in the nation; of the which being still most unjustly deprived, it is now publiquely declared, that they and others seeing their deeds of darknesse brought to light, may be warned, and learn to do justice, and to relieve the oppressed. Also the sounding voyce of the dread of Gods mighty power to all the judges and rulers of the earth, who rise up aginst the Lamb, and to all the host of powers of darknesse who fight against God. By the servants of Christ ... called Humphry Smith. Anthony Melledg. George Henderson. James Potter. Will: Baily. Daniel Baker. John Day. Winifred Newman.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Humphrey, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Simmons, at the Bull and Mouth neer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A narrative, by Humphry Smith, interspersed with letters by Melledge, Henderson, Potter, Baily, Baker, Day, and Newman.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prisoners' writings, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33077:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Fruits of UNRIGHTEOUSNES AND INJUSTICE. Brought forth by <hi>John Bulkley,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Bowrman,</hi> and the reſt of the Rulers in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> againſt the innocent people of God called QUAKERS. Who in words and Writings have often declared their unjuſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ff <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings; As alſo at two Seſſions, and two General Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes holden at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> requiring Juſtice and Equiry, and their Right and Liberty in the Nation; of the which being ſtill moſt unjuſtly deprived, it is now publiquely declared, that they and others ſeeing their deeds of darkneſſe brought to light, may be warned, and learn to do Juſtice, and relieve the OPPRESSED. Alſo the ſounding voyce of the dread of Gods mighty power to all the Judges and Rulers of the Earth, who riſe up againſt the L A M B, and to all the Hoſt of the powers of Darkneſſe who fight againſt God. By the Servants of Chriſt who ſuffers for his Truth, in the common Gaol and Houſe of Correction at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> called</p>
            <list>
               <item>Humphrey Smith.</item>
               <item>Anthony Melledg.</item>
               <item>George Henderſon.</item>
               <item>James Potter.</item>
               <item>Will: Baily.</item>
               <item>Daniel Baker.</item>
               <item>John Day.</item>
               <item>Winifred Newman.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> neer <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33077:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33077:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>is in plain and ſober words, would I have the <hi>Reader</hi> to underſtand, that what is hereafter written, is not publiſhed for the denyal of any righteous government or Governours, nor in contempt of any that rules for God, neither yet in envy towards the perſon of any man, but that the wickedneſs, in them called <hi>Juſtices and Rulers,</hi> and the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which is dayly brought forth, in them who are ſet to do juſtice, might appear; and more eſpecially ſome of them in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> who have oppreſſed the juſt and let the guilty go free, therefore it is both meet and right &amp; faithfulneſs towards God, and plainneſs and love towards the ſouls of them, who have combined together againſt the innocent, to declare open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt that evil principle in them, which moved in their dark minds in ſecret, whereby the workes of darkneſs, hath been brought forth, into publique view, which will now turn back upon that, which is head in them, for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſhame.</p>
            <p>And it is but right and reaſonable, that what oppreſſions by them is laid upon us who dayly ſuffer, the inhumane crul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of unreaſonable men, in our own Nation ſhould be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and recorded, or at leaſt wiſe part of it, in plain and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple words, as was alſo the ſufferings both of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and likewiſe that was written, which the Martyrs ſuffered, by the Biſhops, ungodly Rulers and Popiſh Tyrants, whoſe unrighteous Laws, Edicts and Decrees they could not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, &amp; that wch is unrighteous is alſo now by us denyed, though it be a Law, or a decree which is unjuſt, proceeding from the Prieſts, the unclean ſeed of the Biſhops, and ungodly Rulers, the crooked ſeed of all the former perſecuters, by which Prieſts and Rulers, we have ſuffered ſo much already in <hi>England,</hi> that it is very like before they have filled up their meaſure of blood thirſty Practiſes, and but part thereof gathered up, and recorded, that it will exceed (in the manner and cruelty of it) all the perſecution that yet hath been at any time, in ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33077:3"/> few yeares, conſidering the number, harmleſneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of them who ſuffer, with the manner thereof, and the long impriſonments.</p>
            <p>And <hi>ſecondly</hi> the ſmall cauſes or accuſations which the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors have againſt them, as wearing their hats, or travelling in the high way, or reproving ſin in the gate, market place, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols Temple, or Steeple-houſe, which was the practiſe of the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which is even a ſhame unto Rulers, to lay ſnares for, and ſeek to intrap a harmleſs people about ſuch things.</p>
            <p>And <hi>thirdly</hi> conſidering there unreaſonableneſs therein, by inflicting ſuch great puniſhments, large ſums of money, and long impriſonments, even without limit, until their wills are ſatisfied, only for ſuch ſmall things, as they call contempt, or tranſgreſſion of their Law, which they made to guard the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Prieſts, and ſometimes without any cauſe or any thing at all, to cover their cruelty, but only becauſe we are called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>fourthly</hi> it may appear that theſe Perſecutors, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready exceeded many, in that they Perſecute us for practiſing that which they themſelves profeſs, and practiſe not, and for living in that which they hold in unrighteouſneſs, <hi>Romans</hi> 1: 18. Which is the Truth of God declared in Scripture, and in that they perſecute us, for doing that which <hi>they ſay and do not,</hi> and for being faithful to that, of which even the Prieſts themſelves have long talked, and wear wont to bind people by promiſe, <hi>that they ſhould forſake the Devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked World, and all the ſinful luſts of the fleſh</hi> (then muſt they needs forſake all ſin) <hi>and to believe the Chriſtian Faith</hi> (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſpects no mans perſon) <hi>and to do Gods holy will</hi> (and that is mans ſanctification) <hi>and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> (and that is written in the heart) <hi>and to walk in the ſame all the dayes of their life</hi> (then muſt they needs walk with God and be perfect) and be in this World as he is, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 17. the wch things by the powerful opperation of the immortal word in us, are brought in our meaſures to do, practiſe, and live in and therefore even becauſe we do that, which the blind Prieſts did once teach (and now deny;) Are we now perſecuted, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33077:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> openly reviled, by thoſe coveteous Phariſaical Prieſts, who ſay and unſay, <hi>and ſay and do not,</hi> and preach up a thing one year, and preach it down another, and are of them that Chriſt cryed <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> againſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 23. and herein doth their blindneſs, and cruelty, and the Magiſtrates perſecution, exceed many in former ages.</p>
            <p>And alſo in that we having the Scriptures (which they call their Rule) as <hi>a cloud of witneſſes</hi> for us, but againſt them, and by the power of the Spirit which gave forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are we ready both publique and private, to prove our doctrine, faith, principles and practiſes, to be according to plain Scripture, but the Prophets and Apoſtles of Chriſt, had not a Scripture to prove many things which they did and ſaid, And if this generation, do exceed thoſe that perſecuted them, in perſecuting us, who have the Scriptures, what then, would this generation have done to the Prophets, if they had been in there dayes, who had not the Scriptures? all which being conſidered, and many things more, which might be mentioned, whereby it may appeare, that theſe perſecuting Prieſts and Rulers, have already exceeded all that went before them.</p>
            <p>Again, the <hi>Reader</hi> may conſider, that the members of Chriſt, are not of the World, but are hated and perſecuted by the World, and by our ſufferings, and what is after vvritten, it may appear, that we are not of the World, but hated, reviled and oppreſſed by the World, and by all Sects and Opinions, and all ſorts of People in the World, out of which we are called, by him vvho was before the World, whoſe day <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw, and by his Spirit are we brought to be of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, <hi>who wandred up &amp; down, &amp; had no certain dwelling place and were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, afflicted, tormented,</hi> ſometimes not expecting deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. But following him, who laid down his life, and gave it a Ranſom for many, and off red up his ſoul, and was made perfect, through ſufferings, &amp; he is a perfect example unto us who are called by his grace, and have believed in his name, to whom by the Spirit of the Father, we have been drawn, and his love in our hearts conſtrayneth us to follow him, through great tribulations, though he had not where on to lay his head,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33077:4"/> Neither are we aſhamed to confeſs him before men, who by the Prieſts, Rulers and People, was eſteemed <hi>a Deceiver, a Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of the Law, and a Blaſphemer,</hi> and went about to kill him, becauſe he ſaid God was his Father, unto them who ſaid God was their Father, and therefore crucified him for making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Son of God, and yet they ſaid God was their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>Abraham</hi> was there Father, and yet <hi>did they not do the works of Abraham,</hi> but ſaid, <hi>he had a devil</hi> who did the works of God the Father, which they themſelves could not do, whom afterwards they did not one'y ſeek to kill, but <hi>Lazarus</hi> alſo; <hi>Leaſt all the world ſhould follow him, who is the light of the World, in whom there is no ſin, and in whoſe mouth there is found no guile, who was led as a Lamb dumb,</hi> and by the Prieſts, Rulers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, <hi>was crucified,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light, by whom the world was made,</hi> who is <hi>the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the world, and the Light</hi> of the Lamb <hi>which lighteth every man the cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world,</hi> is by the Prieſts, and Rulers <hi>denyed,</hi> and in them all lyeth <hi>ſlain,</hi> for in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt</hi> our Lord (who is Light) was (and is) ſlain, and are not the Prieſts the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> being found in pride, idleneſs and fulneſs of bread, who can deny it, being they <hi>deny and crucify him, who is the Light,</hi> and have many poor in their Pariſhes in want of bread? And are not the perſecuting Rulers the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> oppreſſing the <hi>Iſrael of God,</hi> ſaving to them, ye are idle, ye are idle, and keep poor people in ſlavery to their corrupt wills, and is it not ſo? do not rich men oppreſs you and draw you before the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seats, and is not the name of God, who is <hi>Light,</hi> blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by them that do, ſo? read and ſee whether the richmen who cauſe to be drawn before the judgment Seat, be not Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, <hi>James</hi> 2. 6, 7. And do not they openly blaſpheme his name who is the Light? and are not the mouths of Prieſts, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and People, filled with blaſphemy againſt him that is the Light? <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 9. and 13. 6. And be not they Blaſpemers who deny him <hi>that makes an end of ſin, and hale them out of their Synagogues, and before Rulers, and their judgement Seats,</hi> who profeſs his name? <hi>John</hi> 16. 2. For in ſpiritual <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> he is ſlain, who is our Lord, even Chriſt the Light, whoſe grave is with the rich, and in the wicked is he buried, whoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33077:4"/> Light in the World reproves the World of ſin, and begins to preach repentance to them that are in it, and teacheth the way of God perfectly, not reſpecting the perſons of men, but ſheweth all things plainly unto them that keep his ſayings, who ſaid <hi>believe in the Light and learn of me,</hi> which Light is in the heart, the which the Prieſts and Rulers with one conſent do ſtrive againſt in themſelves, and with much force and fury, ſeek to ſtop the ſhining forth of it in others, and ſo ſtop that which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the knowledge of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 6. Reſiſting that which is holy in them, for that in them is holy, which in ſecret repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves for ſin, and all that is not holy, the which they ſtill reſiſting are found ſuch, <hi>who crucifie the Son of God a freſh, and put him to open ſhame,</hi> even denying the very end for which he came, wch is <hi>to condemn ſin in the fleſh, and destroy the works of the Devil,</hi> which is ſin, <hi>and to make an end of ſin, and bring in that righteouſneſs which is everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is he, <hi>againſt whom the Rulers</hi> with the Hireling Prieſts, <hi>take councel together, and againſt his anointed ones,</hi> Pſal. 2, 2. 1 John 2. 20. <hi>And wil not have him to reign over them, who ſaves his people from their ſins,</hi> Math. 1. 21. <hi>But all theſe his enemies muſt be ſlain before his face, in this the day of his power,</hi> in which he will threſh all theſe Heathens in his anger <hi>that know not him,</hi> (who finiſheth tranſgreſſion) <hi>and obey not his Goſpel,</hi> which is Gods power, theſe <hi>be will vex in his ſore diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>we unto them that decree unrighteous decrees,</hi> and write grievouſneſs, which they have preſcribed <hi>to turn aſide the needy from judgement,</hi> and take away the right from the poor of the people, <hi>that Widows may be their prey;</hi> and that they may <hi>rob the fatherleſs;</hi> Conſider the Rulers that made unrighteous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, wear <hi>robbers, men-ſtealers.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10. And the Prieſts who conſented together, were <hi>Murtherers, Hoſea</hi> 6. 9. and what will theſe do in the day of viſitation, and in the deſolation which ſhall come from far, to whom vvill they flye for helpe? and where will they leave their glory? Even thus ſhall it be, with them who are without God in the world, oppoſing his Son, and impriſoning his members, <hi>they ſhall bow down under the Priſoners, and fall under the ſlaine,</hi> Eſaiah 10. 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33077:5"/>
            <p>And this is he, even Chriſt <hi>the Light of the world,</hi> againſt whom the Rulers and Prieſts of <hi>Hampſhire</hi> have riſen up, many of them, with much rage and fury, eſpecially <hi>John Bulkley,</hi> juſtice <hi>Hilſley,</hi> (ſo called<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Thomas Bowrman,</hi> and his Prieſt <hi>Thom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> who ſaid <hi>Christ ſwore,</hi> and <hi>Robert Dingly</hi> Prieſt, and Prieſt <hi>Bental,</hi> and <hi>Ellis,</hi> with others ſmote with the tongue, who hearing how the reſt of their brethren, in other counties have with ſtood <hi>the way of God,</hi> and not entertained ſtrangers, <hi>but evil entreated the Servants of the living God,</hi> therefore did that in them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce which is contrary unto God, <hi>and John Bulkley,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Hilſley</hi> did much glory and vaunt themſelves, becauſe of the cruel tyranny which their brethren <hi>(the ſeed of evil doers)</hi> inflicted upon my body (and others of the friends of Chriſt) in other counties by impriſonment, and cruel whipping of the which I am not aſhamed, though they thereby were exalted in that fleſhly glory which luſteth to envy, and in pride and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of ſpirit, from the wrathfull <hi>nature</hi> which ruleth in them, and all perſecuters, who neither <hi>believe in,</hi> nor <hi>receive him that is the Light,</hi> but rebel againſt <hi>him,</hi> and them who preach <hi>his Name;</hi> for <hi>John Bulkley</hi> hath declared often, publick and private, and alſo at the general Affizes before all the people, that he would not that I ſhould come to preach near unto him, and the <hi>ſhe Goaler</hi> hath often ſaid, that it was becauſe I ſhould not preach, that I was kept in Priſon, and truly I preach none other Saviour, <hi>but Chriſt Jeſus who ſaveth from ſin,</hi> and my words, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, and ſufferings are according to Scripture, and ſo <hi>John Bulkley</hi> was ſo far from entertaining ſtrangers, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 2. that he ſought by force, cruelty, impriſonning and whipping, to cauſe <hi>me and others to depart out of his coasts;</hi> (but I am near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and my witneſs is within his walls) though not a ſwine or a dog of his, by me did Periſh, whereby he is manifeſt to be far worſe then the <hi>Gadereens</hi> who <hi>came and beſeeched him to go out of their Coaſts, who is the Light;</hi> and alſo to be of them who crucified him that preached repentance; and <hi>John Bulkley</hi> keepeth the ſwine alive, within his dwellings wallowing in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanes.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing that he, and them before named, and others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mentioned, have let the power of darkneſs ſo blind their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33077:5"/> minds, and harden their hearts, that they have not only lifted up their hands, againſt the innocent, but alſo continued their cruelty, and let their hearts increaſe in hardneſs, like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whereby the Servants of God are ſtill retained in cruel bondage and long inpriſonment, from one ſeſſions to another, and from one affizes, to another, and alſo kept from that liberty in the Priſon, and that Juſtice, which wandring perſons, and thieves and many tranſgreſſors of ſeveral ſorts have had, who were committed to the ſame priſon, and <hi>houſe of correction</hi> ſince we, and alſo releaſed long before us, and that not withſtanding many complaints, and even as it were cryes for Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity have been laid before them, both in words and writings, ſeveral times, both in private and publick, both at aſſize and ſeſſions, whereby many of them in the county that ſhould do juſtice, have been convinced with the Light in there conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, (though they ſtrive againſt it) that our ſufferings have been unjuſt, and unreaſonable, and yet to keep up their own glory, have not done juſtice in releaſing them, whom they knew were oppreſt, becauſe we could not be ſubject to their wills.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let their glory which is to Periſh be defaced, and let their Names be recorded among the reſt of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lamb, and let the ages to come read them with the Light, to be under the power of darkneſs, they having been warned and left without excuſe, that both their Actions and our ſufferings might the more plainly appear, and that they and all others who are ſet to do juſtice, might take heed of raſhneſs, in juſtice and envy, or ſmiting with the fiſt of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they might come to know ſomething meek, lowly, upright, juſt and ſober in them, by it to be guided, in the fear of the Lord, to execute true juſtice, and to do unto all men as they would be done unto.</p>
            <p>Therefore are ſome few of their unjuſt actions, and ſome Copies of our papers after written, paſſing by much of what hath been already printed, (in a Book titled <hi>the true and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Rule)</hi> and citing ſome few things among many, which may ſignify much of their injuſtice and cruelty, the which that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33077:6"/> they and others may turn from, and do that which is juſt and right, let them feel Gods witneſs in them, and read that which followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>South Haumpton. <hi>A Copy of a Mittimus.</hi> To the keepers of the common Goal for this County of <hi>Winton,</hi> or to his Deputy.</head>
                  <p>I <hi>ſend you herewithall the bodies of</hi> Humphry Smith, <hi>of</hi> Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn <hi>in the County of</hi> Heriford; Anthony Melledge <hi>of</hi> Lime, <hi>in the County of</hi> Dorſet, <hi>and</hi> William Bayly <hi>of for that they have been charged before me, with ſeveral miſdemeanors by them committed at</hi> Poulnar <hi>in the Pariſh of</hi> Ringwood, <hi>and for that they refuſed to finde ſureties for their appearance at the next gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Aſſizes, ſo be held for this County, and in the mean time to be of the good behaviour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe are therefore to require you to receive them, the ſaid</hi> Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phry Smith, Anthony Melledge, <hi>and</hi> William Bayly, <hi>into your cuſtody, them ſafely keep in your common Goal, until they ſhall from thence be delivered by due courſe of Law, and hereof faile you not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my hand and Seal <date>the 27. day of <hi>February,</hi> 1657.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>John Bulkley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>William Baylys <hi>anſwer to the Mittimus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEre the ground of our commitment to priſon was founded upon a lye, and ſo from that of the father of lyes in <hi>John Bulkley,</hi> for at the preſent time, there was many people who can yet witneſs, that not one of them in the leaſt, did accuſe or charge me of any evil in the leaſt, nor any one miſdemeanor by me committed, neither was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> at <hi>Poulnar</hi> at the time intended, in the mittimus.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Copy of a Letter to</hi> John Bulkley.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THis I ſay before thee, in the preſence of the Lord God, who will plead the cauſe of the oppreſſed, and in due time will clear my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33077:6"/> innocency before thy eyes, and all the world, and that witneſs of God, the righteous Judge that is in thee will make thee know that I now ſuffer without cauſe, and whether it be according to equity and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous Judgement, to commit a man to priſon, or cauſe him to ſuffer, without tranſgreſſing any just and righteous Law, I leave to that of God in thy Conſcience to judge, to take up a man who was going in a journey and in and about honeſt imployment, in the ſight of God and man; but if thou art not cauſed by that of God in thy Conſcience, to free me of my outward bonds, and innocent ſufferings, I am content to lay down my life, for his ſake, who in due time will ariſe and clear my innocency, in this my faithful ſuffering.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Called William Bayly.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>John Bulkleys anſwer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WIlliam Bayly,</hi> I take no delight in your impriſonment, but ſhall be ready to take your friend <hi>Harris,</hi> or any fit perſons ſecurity for your abode at home, without wandering abroad as a Teacher, to which you have no warrantable call, but onely to follow your honeſt and Lawful occaſions, which you have a freedome to do; touching your commitment, your refuſal to give a ready and free account of your place of abode, accompanyed with termes of high diſreſpect, and contempt to. Authority, brought you under commitment, when others of your Company carrying themſelves civilly, were diſmiſſed, if you belong to God, I truſt in due time he will reſcue you from the Spirit of error, you lye under, to which ſhall be contributed my prayers, and Chriſtian endevours.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours John Bulkley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Reply.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THou ſayeſt I have a freedome to follow my Lawful occaſions, the which I was travelling about, and had continued in, if thou had not ſent me to priſon, and called it wandering abrad, and keept me in priſon, from my Lawfull occaſions, wch are abroad, unleſs</hi> I will give ſecurity for my abode at home, <hi>from whence I came but the day before to the Pariſh where I was born, out of which Pariſh, thou ſenteſt me to priſon, with others as a wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; and now thou wouldeſt have me</hi> give ſecurity to ſtay at home,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33077:7"/> 
                     <hi>and ſo to ſtay from the Pariſh in which I was born; and I did give thee an account, that I was born in that Pariſh, and ſo thou canst not cover thy ſelfe, with ſaying, that</hi> I refuſed to give thee an accu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and then thou mentions termes of</hi> high diſreſpect, <hi>brought me under com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment, &amp; in the</hi> mittimus <hi>thou ſaid</hi> it was for ſeveral miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors done at Poulnar, <hi>though both are falſe, and then wherein art thou to be</hi> reſpected? <hi>and then to cover thy own reſpecting of perſons, thou ſaid</hi> others carrying themſelves civilly were diſmiſſed, <hi>which others were</hi> John Fry <hi>and</hi> William Fry <hi>who may be men of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds a year who with us, did not reſpect thy perſon though thou aideſt reſpect theirs, and ſaid to</hi> John Fry, <hi>thou would ſhew him all the civill reſpect as may be, and then though thou ſay,</hi> I lye under a ſpirit of error, <hi>yet thou writ</hi> yours John Bulkley, <hi>which if true, then thou art his that is in error; but being not true, it turnes back upon thee, and as for</hi> thy prayers, <hi>I ſay as he did whoſe Eyes Chriſt opened, to ſee beyond all the Hypocrites, who caſt out him, who ſaid we know that God heareth not ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>It may be obſerved that <hi>William Bayly</hi> was born in the Pariſh that <hi>John Bulkley</hi> dwelleth, and ſent him to priſon from, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his folly and madneſs to all men may appear, and that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſecurity of him to ſtay from that Pariſh where he was born, and ſeveral people at the ſame time acquainted him that he was born there; wherefore J. B. was aſhamed to write the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh name in the <hi>Mittimus,</hi> but left it vvith a blank, as may be ſeen.</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>Mittimus</hi> mentions his commiting to be <hi>for ſeveral miſdemeanors,</hi> and in his next paper he ſaith it was <hi>for refuſing to give a ready account of his place of abode, with termes of high diſreſpect,</hi> and at the aſſizes, he ſaid it was <hi>becauſe he would not tell his name;</hi> and the fourth time he ſaid it was <hi>becauſe he would not ſpeak,</hi> that he ſent him to priſon, (which was all far from Truth) and if he did not ſpeak, how is it that he gave <hi>termes of high diſreſpect</hi>? may not all people ſee the madneſs and folly of <hi>John Bulkley,</hi> who was ſomewhat offended, becauſe it was tould him (though not by <hi>William Bayly)</hi> that he was a ſilly man when he began this blinde perſecution, with unfound words and actions? the which if his words, writings, and unjuſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33077:7"/> actions, hath not already made manifeſt, it may farther appear, when his inſide is farther diſcovered.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Copy of a Letter to John Bulkley.</head>
                  <p>WHat canſt thou have more then our lives? having firſt deprived us of our right and liberty in the Nation, and taken men up from their Lawful buſineſs, which they were going upon, for the maintenance of them and their families, and ſend them to priſon without the leaſt ground of offence, according to Law, or any Law tranſgreſſed, and in priſon keep them, until their bodies had ſuffered ſo much (in a little time) that thou thy ſelfe took notice, that their bodies were altered, and countenances changed, and then thou promiſed to ſpeak to the judge for them, who did not ſeek it of thee, <hi>but gave up their bodies as a living ſacrifice,</hi> &amp; then in ſtead of ſpeaking to the Judge, thou did vent forth what thou couldſt againſt them, &amp; that which was falſe to (at the aſſize) whereby now they who (are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent) are caſt into <hi>Bridewel,</hi> and lyable to whipping, blowes, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, lowſineſs, and the want of all neceſſaries, and what ever may be inflicted upon our weak bodies, by moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and ungodly men, who before we were thus commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their power, did inflict ſo much upon us that we were ſometimes hardly able to bear it, as thy own man was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſenſible of, and the Light of Chriſt in thy own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will let thee ſee the ſame, though we were not apt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, but leave it to the Lord, who will plead our cauſe, and clear our innocency in the day of his power.</p>
                  <p>And this would I lay before thine eyes, that thou may be left without excuſe, that <hi>William Bayly</hi> having had an ague long, and not forth of the town (he dwelt in) a long time, and now hardly able to go, though with us about his Lawful occations, &amp; ſince he came to priſon taken much cold, with what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; if he or either of us periſh under thy cruelty will not his blood be required at thy hand, in the day when the wo will come upon all them, that offend the innocent Lambs of Jeſus Chriſt? and what is it now, that thou ſeeks after, but onely our lives, or impriſonment, until death? being thou haſt got
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33077:8"/> an order, to keep us in <hi>Bridewel</hi> until we promiſe to go (or ſtay at) home, thou knowing from us, that we cannot make that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and if thou wouldeſt make mens own houſes their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by confining them thereunto, and not go forth upon their occaſions, then ſhould we loſe that right and liberty which we long fought for.</p>
                  <p>Therefore conſider thy actions, and bring not innocent blood upon thy head, for by the zealous profeſſors did Chriſt ſuffer, and ſufferings is our portion, <hi>but wo to them by whom the offence commeth,</hi> for the Lord God of life and power, will plead our cauſe, and a witneſs we have for us, in thy own Conſcience, which when thou art alone will plead our innocency and in ſecret reprove thee for having a hand againſt the members of Chriſt, of the which we are, who now ſuffer under thy will, though not by the tranſgreſſion of any Law of <hi>England,</hi> in the which we are free born, and known by the Names of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>H.S. A.M. W.B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Copy of <hi>John Bulkleys</hi> Letter to the (woman) Goaler.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Mrs. Hobs.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Am informed that the three <hi>Quakers,</hi> are often puniſhed by <hi>whipping,</hi> which though I ſuppoſe it done in obedience to the Judges laſt order, whereof I am ignorant, being then abſent from the bench, or elſe that you would not do it, yet in regard of their weak and ſickly condition, as I am informed, I deſire you to forbear any farther corporal correction, and to afford them convenient accommodation, till the approaching ſeſſions, when perhaps they may ſatisfy the bench, that they will return home<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and forbear rambling abroad; this from your Friend</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Bulkley.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <date>March the 26. 1658</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We having made it appear that we are no wanderers, thy own hand writing will ſtand a witneſs againſt thy ſelf, and for the innocency of our ſuffering, under thy corrupt will, who having no evil to charge us with, doeſt keep our weake bodies under affliction; until we give ſecurity or promiſe to ſtay at home, and we do not read of any ſuch blind perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33077:8"/> as thee in all the Scriptures and here all people may ſee the fruits of thy wickedneſs, who haſt cauſed the harmles Lambs of Chriſt to be ſo afflicted, being ſick &amp; in priſon, and the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite might well be affraid, leaſt we ſhould be perſecuted to death, and our innocent blood come upon his head, but though thy heart was ſomewhat judged at the time, when thou write thy Letter to that uncleane beaſtly Woman thou calls <hi>Mrs. Hobs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> yet ſoon after thy heart was hardned again like <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="italic">At the Seſſions following, <hi>John Bulkley</hi> ſent his Clark to us, to ſee if we would promiſe to goe home, and ſo to releaſe us; if we could but onely have ſpoken ſome ſuch words to ſatisfie their wills, the which we durſt not do; And therefore being retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Priſon, we writ to them concerning ſuch a promiſe, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
               <body>
                  <p>WE are not only free-born of <hi>England,</hi> but we have alſo purchaſed our freedome in the Nation, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation thereof with many years hard ſervice, the loſſe of the lives of many hundreds, the ſpoyling of much goods, and the ſhedding of much blood in the late war, by which at laſt the Lord overturned them, who then ſought to enſlave our perſons, and infringe our liberty in the Nation, in the which liberty now, we do expect to <hi>worſhip God in ſpirit, and in truth,</hi> according to the Scriptures, and to ſpeak the word of the Lord as any one of his ſervants is moved by his ſpirit; &amp; we alſo expect liberty to follow our employments, which are honeſt in the fight of God, and all men that fear his Name, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to be a praiſe unto ſuch, and by the wholſome Lawes of the Nation, us herein to defend; <hi>England</hi> being as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> mans houſe, or home; and wherein any of us are deprived of theſe things, we are deprived of our Rights, and infringed of our Liberties in the Nation; the which done, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will be an evill example unto other Nations, amongſt whom alſo ſometimes I had, and have buſineſſe, I having been much at Sea, for almoſt twenty years, and have ſome occaſions at, and beyond Sea at this preſent; and I have alſo ſeverall lawfull oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33077:9"/> in divers parts of the Land; about which I now tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, was taken up, and ſent to Priſon, and my horſe lay at charge by me, my goods which I had with me being ſent up to <hi>London,</hi> whether I ſhould alſo go, to make ſale of it, or paſſe my ſelfe with it; and more over Sea, ſome ſuch buſineſſe at Sea and Land, being my preſent employment, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of my ſelf and family, all which I am now deprived of, and kept in <hi>Bridewell,</hi> becauſe I cannot promiſe to go home, and ſo leave my employment and buſineſſe undone, which is the way to ruinate men and their families.</p>
                  <p>And as for <hi>William Baily,</hi> he was travelling but to <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton,</hi> upon ſeverall lawfull occaſions, but before he came there, was taken up with me, and brought to a Priſon which is further off his home then he intended to go, and in it kept from his home many weeks longer then he did intend to ſtay, and there yet kept from his buſineſſe, becauſe he cannot make a promiſe to go home, and is not this the way to make us ſervants and ſlaves to mens wills?</p>
                  <p>And as for <hi>Humphrey Smith,</hi> though his Wife came (to the Seſſions) many miles from her habitation, and brought two men and a horſe for her Husband to ride away with her, yet is he alſo kept in priſon, becauſe he cannot promiſe to go home; and which of you is it that can promiſe what to do on the morrow?</p>
                  <p>Therefore out of all theſe promiſes, we ſtand in ſubmiſſion to the will of the Lord, <hi>Knowing that they who will live godly muſt ſufler perſecution:</hi> And ſeeing we have broke no Law, nor intend any evill againſt any man or woman, but abide in all watchfulneſſe, <hi>to keep a conſcience void of offence towards God and man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Anthony Mellidge.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Paper being little regarded by them that are ſet to do Juſtice, for they ſtill kept us in priſon, becauſe we durſt not make a promiſe, wch is more then they themſelves can wel do, if they ſtood in the feare of God, as may appear by him who was called Juſtice <hi>Cobb,</hi> who ſate as Judge at the Seſſions, whoſe heart was then and there, and afterwards hardned againſt us
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33077:9"/> like <hi>Pharaoh, refuſing to let us go;</hi> but ſuddenly in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not long after, the Lord cut him off, and then what promiſe could he himſelfe perform? Oh! that this might be a warning to all oppreſſing Rulers who are as graſſe.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
               <body>
                  <head>A Copie of another Paper.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute> You who are ſet to do Juſtice, and to be Miniſters of known Laws, and are to relieve the oppreſſed, and do that which is juſt in the ſight of God, and all men that feare his name, and ſhould be a terrour to ſuch as do evill, and a praiſe to ſuch as do well, which is according to that of God in all conſciences.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THis we ſay unto you, that ſince we have been taken from our Callings and Imployments, and impriſoned, and alſo cauſed to be kept in outward bonds by ſome of you; we have ſeen ſuch as have been accuſed of divers manners of Theft, Witchcraft, and Murther, receive their ſentence, or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to your Law, or otherwiſe quit, releaſed, and freed out of outward bonds.</p>
                  <p>And we have ſeen a man whom we have known to be an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle perſon, and a drunkard, and ſo a tranſgreſſor of the Law, committed to the houſe of Correction for wandring or idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and received his puniſhment, and releaſed. Likewiſe a Tinker committed to the houſe of Correction, received his puniſhment, and releaſed. Alſo two men and a boy that came out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who appeared to be wanderers, and ſuſpective perſons, who ſaid they had no money, and were tranſgreſſors alſo of the Law by fighting, if they were not Papiſts, and theſe alſo (as the other) were committed ſince we, and releaſed in ſhort time, though we ſtill kept priſoners.</p>
                  <p>And this alſo we ſay unto you; that if we have broken, or tranſgreſſed any Law, or if any evill is, or can be proved againſt us, then our bodies are ready, and we are willing to ſuffer the puniſhment according to the Law, for any ſuch offence if char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon us, that the Law being ſatisfied, we might have our liberty again (as others) to travell about our lawfull oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33077:10"/>
                  <p>And this would we know of you: Firſt, by what Law of God or man, we are herein deprived of that right and liberty which Theeves, Murtherers, Witches, Wanderers, and other known tranſgreſſors have.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, what Law you have to keep us in the houſe of Correction, untill we engage or promiſe to go home. If you have any ſuch law, let us know it, that we might ſubmit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, for we are ready to ſubmit unto all your Laws, either actively by obedience thereunto, or paſſively by ſuffering un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, for a teſtimony againſt that which is unjuſt; <hi>but where there is no law there is no tranſgreſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, whether you do intend to keep our bodies in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon untill death, unleſſe we purchaſe our liberty by ſpeaking words, of <hi>promiſing to go home,</hi> ſeeing you hear already that we cannot make ſuch promiſes, knowing no law requiring us thereunto.</p>
                  <p>An anſwer to theſe things would we willingly receive in writing from ſome of you, that both your ground and your end might from you be knovvn, vvherefore vve are deprived of our right and liberty in the Nation, and kept in long impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>At the Aſſizes, vvhen the Judge vvas about to ſend us avvay, a Juſtice (ſo called) ſpake to him that vve might be put in the houſe of Correction: And the ſame day vvhen <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Darby</hi> vvere examined by the Judge, the youngeſt of the <hi>Darbies</hi> could not then give a ready anſvver; then one called a Juſtice bid him ſay that he vvas going into the Countrey to ſee friends, and ſo joyned vvith a high-vvay Robber, and before all the Court vvould have taught him to make lyes his refuge, who was afterwards (with his brother) condemned for high way robbing; but being reprieved ſince, with others, have much abuſed us, and ſo they neither ſuffer according to your Law, by which they were to dye, neither yet do they ſuffer accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the righteous Law of God, which is <hi>to restore four fold.</hi> And moreover, they and ſuch as them have liberty to act even almoſt all manner of deſperate wickedneſſe in the Priſon night &amp; day, by which our ſouls do ſuffer, and ſuch as theſe, one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Juſtice ſpake as for, and we who fear the Lord, another
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33077:10"/> called a Juſtice ſpake as againſt, whereby we were put into, and kept in the houſe of Correction, and ſo cauſe us to ſuffer beyond the extent of any law: And is not this according to them, who ſaid, and did releaſe <hi>Barabbas,</hi> and crucifie the <hi>Juſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore ye men, minde the witneſſe of God in all your conſciences, and come into his fear, that you may love mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, do juſtly, and walk humbly, that the juſt in every one of you may have dominion, and then the impriſoned members of Chriſt will not need to cry unto you for juſtice and equity. Your anſwer to them you may return, who certainly are the ſervants of God in outward bonds. (but the <hi>Darbies</hi> are ſince releaſed.)</p>
                  <p>Now let all peoples mouths be ſtopt for ever, from ſaying we that are called <hi>Quakers</hi> are not ſubject to Authority, nor obedient to the Law; for if we for conſcience ſake cannot actually be obedient to an unjuſt Law, yet if paſſively, we willingly ſuffer the puniſhment, which that Law ſaith is to be inflicted upon him that doth not keep it, then therein is that Law alſo by us fulfilled, and hath no more power over us, who herein are obedient to Authority, <hi>and ſubmit to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake:</hi> But our ſouls are <hi>ſubject to the higher power, which rules over all them who are in the perſecuting powers of darkneſſe,</hi> who though they be ſet to be Miniſters of a Law, and acting without a Law, contrary to the Law, <hi>are found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves tranſgreſſors of the Law,</hi> being out of the feare and Law of God, and out of the Law of the Nation; And ſo they are far out, and from that of which Authority conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtech, and indeed out of all power both of God and man, in their own wills, ruling with cruelty over others in the power of Darkneſs.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>We having thus endeavoured by uſing all means, which is juſt in the ſight of God, for our right and liberty, and having remained cloſe Priſoners many weekes, without convenient place to worke, though we were committed to the work-houſe, we then endeavoured to get
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33077:11"/> room and liberty to work with our hands, and therefore one of us did write unto him, by whom we were unjustly committed, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>John Bulkley,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THou alone art the cauſe of my impriſonment almoſt theſe nine weeks, in which I have almoſt ſuffered to the death of my body, being alſo ſicke when I was brought to priſon among thoſe, in whoſe company wert thou but one night, it would make thy fleſh to tremble, and grieve thy ſoul (if thou feared God) to hear &amp; ſee the filthy converſation of the wicked from day to day, the like wickedneſſe I do believe was not found in <hi>Sodome,</hi> nor in the old World whom God deſtroyed with an utter overthrow. Oh! conſider a little in the feare of the righteous God, who is the righteous Judge of all mankind, whether thou haſt done unto me, as thou wouldſt be done unto, who am a ſufferer under thy hand of oppreſſion <hi>(for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake)</hi> both in body and ſoule, being grieved and vexed with the abominations that I daily hear and ſee, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and unreaſonableneſs of them by whom we ſuffer, where alſo we are deprived of all outward liberty without cauſe, which in the day of viſitation the witneſſe of God in thee for me ſhall witneſſe, and this action of thine againſt the innocent in that day will be as a milſtone about thy neck, and as a fiery flaming worm to eate thy fleſh: Yea, and if thou proceed in the evill that is in thy hands, and repent not ſpeedily, when thou wilt think peace to thy ſelfe, then will thy ſudden deſtruction come as in a moment from the Lord God, who is a ſwift wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt all iniquity and unrighteouſneſſe of men without reſpect of perſons.</p>
                  <p>Therefore once more conſider, and weigh thy actions in the juſt ballance, even by the light of Chriſt in thy conſcience, which will let thee ſee, <hi>by what meaſure thou meteſt, it will be meaſured to thee again.</hi> And this is right, and according as God will judg and reward every man, to which that of God in thy conſcience do witneſſe, though for a time thou mayſt ſtrive to hide and vaile it, for the honour of the worlds ſake, and the love of the praiſe of men; but what will this avail or profit thee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33077:11"/> in the day wherein thou wilt be juſtly weighed, and tryed, then to be found by the Judge of all the Earth to be a perſecutor of his people, and anointed ones, for <hi>whoſe ſake he will rebuke Kings,</hi> and will <hi>fight our battels, and plead our cauſe in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:</hi> Therefore do we <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> in quietneſſe <hi>to ſee his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and a freedome from the oppreſſion of all wickedneſſe, and wicked men, under whom for a time the juſt do ſuffer. I do not vvrite to thee, as to complain to thee, but am contented in my ſufferings (for <hi>my God heares the ſighing of his priſoners)</hi> neither do I expect any thing from thee but equity and juſtice, of vvhich thou beareſt the name, but acteſt not in the lifethere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo in the day of try all vvilt be found among the hypocrites, bearing the name of that thou neither art, nor liveſt in. I muſt deale plainly vvith thee, though under thy povver I ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death, this I can ſay, I have no envy to thy perſon, nor to any man upon the earth, God is my vvitneſſe; neither dare I give flattering titles to any man, for in ſo doing I ſhould be condemned by the vvitneſſe of God in my conſcience, vvhoſe peace is more gain to me, then all the riches and glory of this periſhing World; but this I lay to thy charge juſtly (vvho art out of the ſtate of Gods elect, to vvhich that of God in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience eternally ſhall vvitneſſe (to vvit) my ſufferings unjuſtly by thy means, vvith the reſt of my dear brethren, vvhoſe dear life in innocency is hid from the wiſe of the world) in that thou took us vvho vvere about honeſt and lavvfull occaſions, and ſent us to priſon (vvho intend no harm to any) and aftervvard ſent me vvord in vvriting, that to follovv my lavvfull occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions I had a freedome, of vvhich before thou had deprived me; but this vvill not hide thy deceit and envy againſt Gods people. For I was in the Town in which I naturally was born, who there was neither found acting nor ſpeaking any thing that was unlawfull or diſhoneſt (for ſuch things I hate) but thou acted toward me that which is diſhoneſt, and unlawfull in ſending me to priſon, without the breach of any Law; and is this a ſmall thing to ſend a man from his honeſt and lawfull employment (by which he hath his ſubſiſtance) to a wicked and ungodly place, to be kept Priſoner in the common Gaol, where we are deprived both of our outward liberty and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33077:12"/> for the maintenance of our bodies (which by thy means hath greatly ſuffered) neither do we know of ſo much liberty as to ſend for work to work at my Trade, where it may be had, and ſent for to Priſon, where I being kept, and like to remain, am willing to work with my hands, if room and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty I might have. Therefore I would know from thee, if thou wilt ſend me an Order in Writing under thy hand, for me to have room and liberty here to work at my lawfull calling, and alſo that ſome friend of mine may have liberty to come in and out with my work, and not be abuſed; and to this thing I do expect a ſpeedy anſwer from thee; for it is unreaſonable that I ſhould be kept from my work, and my work from me, who have done no evill, who am of the world called</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From the Houſe of Correction in the common Gaol of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> 
                        <date>the 3d day of the 3d moneth, 1658.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>William Baily.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>William Baily</hi> alſo, having endeavoured, though with charge and trouble, to have Wool bought and made ready, and to have all things needfull for him, and more of us to work at his Trade, and having hereby obtained an Order to the Gaoler, that he might have room and liberty, and things convenient ſuffered to be brought in unto him, yet did the Goaler hinder him of having coals, without which he could not work, and thereby for a time, his work (being in all things ready) lay ſtill and ſuffered loſs; and ſo ſhe that ſhould keep idle perſons committed to the Houſe of Correction on vvork, doth neither do that, but alſo hinder him from his lawfull labour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to her place, and alſo contrary to two Juſtices Orders, and hereby many may be ſatisfied alſo concerning things that falſe Accuſers have caſt upon us, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> that we are idle, or refuſe to work at our lawfull Callings, yet to be ſet on work as idle perſons, and tranſgreſſors are, at their wills, or their work belonging to their houſe of Correction, we deny for ever.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:33077:12"/>
            <p rend="italic">Here followeth a Relation of <hi>Daniel Bakers</hi> ſufferings, lately a Captain in the Service for Liberty, but by a filthy Prieſt is now caſt into the ſame <hi>Bridewell</hi> with me, whom he came from <hi>London</hi> to viſit (and <hi>George Henderſon</hi> with him) who hath written ſomething of their unjuſt impriſonment, with his own hand next in order.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
               <body>
                  <p>IN the third moneth, 58. it came into my heart to travel from my Family to viſit the ſuffering members of Chriſt in <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> priſon; but when according to the will of the Lord I came to the Priſon door, both I and my friend <hi>G. H.</hi> were not onely long kept out of the Priſon, at the door, but alſo there much abuſed by <hi>John Grove</hi> a Turn-key, <hi>Chriſtopher Darby,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and afterwards was I moved to paſſe into the Iſe of <hi>Wight,</hi> contrary to my own will, and it came to paſſe on the 19th, of the ſame moneth, the fourth day of the vveek (vvhich vvas ſet apart (as the hypocrites and prophane ſaid) for a day of publique Humiliation) that for my love vvas I then evil intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, beaten, and haled forth of the ſynagogue, and before a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; but it's no nevv thing (eſpecially in theſe dayes) for Prieſts, Rulers, and people (curſed children) vvho obey the povvers of darkneſſe, to ſmite the innocent and guiltleſſe vvith the fiſt of vvickedneſſe, even upon the days of their Faſts, buffetting and halling ſuch, vvhoſe pure conſciences are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed tovvards God, out of their Idols Temples, Synagogues, or Steeple-houſes, before Magiſtrates, and caſt them into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vvhere they are thruſt into holes and dungeons, even as it hath been fulfilled upon this body of mine, vvhoſe blood much hath been ſhed, vvith my bones ſhattered to pieces in the late Wars, for the juſt right and liberty of ſuch vvho feare the Lord God, and of this Common-vvealth; but behold O ye ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-minded ones! hovv the ravenous Beaſts of the field, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the moſt High ſeek to devour, perſecute, deſtroy, and make a prey upon the ſervants of the Lord, vvho is novv ariſing as a Gyan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> refreſht with wine, to confound, overturn, and daſh in pieces as a potters veſſell, his enemies, as in the dayes of old.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33077:13"/>
                        <head>A Copie of a Writing ſent to <hi>Robert Dingly,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Brixton</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Robert Dingly,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>SEeing there there are many Deceivers in the world, and eſpecially in this Nation of</hi> England, <hi>I being one who am a friend to the Truth (and ſound Doctrine) and a lover of peoples ſoules, even of thine (amongſt the reſt) who haſt been a Teacher of the people ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It lyeth upon me for the Truths ſake, to deſire thee (if thou be a Miniſter of Chriſt) to appoint a meeting either publique or private, but if it be poſſible in publique, that there it may be truly proved by plain Scripture, (without adding or diminiſhing, in the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all people) who are the deceivers, and who are the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>I deſire thee to ſend me thy anſvver by vvay of Writing. <hi>Brixton,</hi> 
                              <date>the nineteenth of the third moneth, 58.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>I am thy friend ſo far as thou obeyeſt and loveſt the Truth, Daniel Baker.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>My friend <hi>George Henderſon</hi> (vvho vvas vvith me) carried this Writing to the Prieſts houſe, vvho after ſome time ſpake vvith him (to vvit) Prieſt <hi>Dingly,</hi> vvho in his envious rage and fury abuſed him, and our friends with reproachful, lying, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious ſpeeches, and refuſed to write an Anſwer; onely here is vvhat came from his ovvn mouth, vvhich ſpake from the unclean ſpirit which is head in him, as doth appear, let the honeſt Reader judge with that of God in his conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Now before my friend gave this Prieſt the Letter, he asked his name, ſaying, is thy name <hi>Robert Dingly?</hi> (in ſuch plain true words according to Scripture) he anſwered in ſcorn, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>thy name? thy name? I thought it was ſuch fools as thee art,</hi> with ſundry other vain filthy ſpeeches; I <hi>ſhall take a courſe with thee, ſaid he, I ſhall ſend thee to priſon</hi> (mark) <hi>G. H.</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>I matter not thy impriſonment;</hi> ſo the Prieſt took the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33077:13"/> Letter, and began to read (mark) and ſaid, <hi>We fools deſire thee to give us a meeting.</hi> Now theſe words was not written in the Paper (as the Reader may ſee above) but came from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirit (head in him) then my friend asked him why he did lye; the Prieſts anſwer was, ſaying, <hi>I know the Devill is in you all.</hi> After which ſaying he fled away, and would give no further anſvver, only bid his man put him out of doors, and bolt the door after him.</p>
                  <p>I being in the fear of the Lord (in love to the ſeed of the God of <hi>Abraham)</hi> with bowels of compaſſion was moved to appear at the <hi>Steeple houſe, G. H.</hi> went with me, where I came in amongſt the multitude peaceably, and in the dread of the Lord, and ſo continued for the ſpace of about halfe an hour, and then ſpake a few words with tears, the Lord (whom I ſerve with my ſpirit) knoweth my innocency, that I was free from envy or malice to any one mans perſon upon the face of the whole earth; but I was hindred in the work of the Lord, the Prieſt immediately called out (being in his Pulpit in <hi>Cains</hi> nature) ſaying to the mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tude, <hi>take him away, take him away,</hi> who with violence abuſed us both, beating with a great ſtaffe, kicking and throwing us down, and haled us forth of their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, or <hi>Steeple houſe,</hi> and brought us before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (ſo called) who had ſo much regard with compulſion, to have his perſon reſpected, and honoured, by commanding our hats to be taken off our heads, which was laid in the duſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us (mark) a true figure where his honour ſhall be layd (as I then ſhevved him) ſo that even that which would make him truly honourable, was and is lightly eſteemed by him. I could wiſh that he and all the Magiſtrates in <hi>England,</hi> would lay it to heart to know, that before honour is humility, and that which is meek is low in the heart, and <hi>is the higher power every ſoul is to be ſubject to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iting (above written) which was ſent to Prieſt <hi>Dingly</hi> (before I appeared in the Steeple-houſe) was read before <hi>Tho: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>owrman</hi> (called a Juſtice) his Prieſt <hi>Tomkins</hi> being with him, and wreſted the Scripture to prove that Chriſt did ſwear, like a blinde blaſphemous ſottiſh bruit; Many other perſons were there preſent at the ſame time when we were examined,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33077:14"/> and moſt unjuſtly committed to Priſon by the ſaid <hi>Thomas Bowrman,</hi> who was ſo deaf and blinde, he could not hear his ſottiſh Prieſt ſpeak blaſphemy, neither ſee the tranſgreſſor, to lay the ſword upon his head within and without; but being under the power of darkneſſe, the ſword vvas laid upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent both vvithin and vvithout.</p>
                  <p>Alſo he cauſed three men to ſvvear againſt us, contrary to Chriſts Doctrine (vvho ſaid, <hi>ſwear not at all)</hi> and of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples vvhich follovved him in the life; vvhich taught the ſame Doctrine, ſaying, <hi>Above all things my brethren ſwear not, leſt you fall into condemnation.</hi> And if <hi>Thomas Bowrman;</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Thomkins</hi> had been come to <hi>Chriſt the light of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> [as I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned vvich them vvhen I vvas falſely accuſed before him,] and ſo abide in his Doctrine, then he nor any ſuch dare not go out of his Doctrine, neither cauſe others to tranſgreſſe. I wiſh he may finde a place of repentance with the reſt of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the time, before it be too late, left ſuch be then cut down as fruitleſſe trees which cumbers the ground.</p>
                  <p>Now I appeal to that of God in all conſciences to judg, if ſo that <hi>R. Dingly</hi> had bin a Miniſter of Chriſt, &amp; had preacht, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed, and lived in the life, walking in the doctrine of the light of the Son of God, whether or no it did not highly concern him, with the <hi>ſpirit of meekneſſe and ſound doctrine,</hi> in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of all people (as it was deſired) to convince the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers [in ſuch perillous times as theſe] and whether a Miniſter of Chriſt the Light, would not have greatly rejoyced to have done the will of the Lord in the worke of the Miniſtry for the truths ſake, that the honeſt ſimple-hearted might be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified, and ſo to know how to beware of woolviſh hirelings, ſuch as the holy Prophets, Chriſt, his Apoſtles, Miniſters, and Saints did, and do witneſſe againſt, as the Scripture of Truth beareth teſtimony, even againſt them <hi>who ſeeks their gain from their quarters, eating the fat, drinking the ſweet, cloathing with the wool,</hi> and <hi>feeding themſelves</hi> (without fear) <hi>and not the flock who are kept ever learning, and not able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> and ſo deſtroyed for lack of knowledg, by ſuch <hi>gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dogs which can never have enough, Iſa.</hi> 56. The latter end, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch as <hi>Robert Dingly</hi> is, who as it doth appear manifeſtly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33077:14"/> to all that fear the Lord God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> how that if he had not been in the ſame footſteps of the falſe Prophets and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, and alſo aſhamed of his Doctrine, practice, maintenance and converſation. I know he durſt not have been ſo envious, raging with fury and madneſſe, running to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall weapons, to the Magiſtrate, before whom he, with the reſt of his uncircumciſed generation work their lying wonders, to captivate, priſon, and perſecute the juſt, guiltleſſe, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, even unto death, as many of this ravenous, curſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious ſeed of evill doers have done (and daily do) who rebel againſt the Light, and with greedineſle are haſtning to fill up their meaſures of Iniquity in their unclean Tabernacles in theſe their days, woe be to them. <hi>A terrible and dreadful day of darkneſſe is haſtning over them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo I ſay, let the ſober minded conſider and obſerve this with me, its written, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2, ſaying, <hi>behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you</hi> (to wit the Saints) <hi>into priſon to try you,</hi> ſo that its manifeſt, the Devil ſpake by the mouth of his unclean Prophet <hi>R. D.</hi> who ſaid to our friend, <hi>I ſhall take a courſe with thee, I ſhall ſend thee to Priſon;</hi> ſo that from the unclean falſe Prophet, the voice went forth, the beaſt being ready alſo, to do or execute his Maſters will, <hi>(who is the Prince of darkneſs,)</hi> and by his power to uphold the falſe Prophet, and ſaid to us <hi>whoſe meat and drink it is to do the will of our heavenly Father</hi> (in our ſeveral meaſures) <hi>bearing teſtimony againſt the beaſt and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and all deeds of darkneſs whatſoever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſay <hi>Thomas Bowrman</hi> ſaid to us by the ſame Spirit (which is head in the Prieſt and himſelfe, and threatned to caſt into priſon, which was alſo performed,) <hi>you think you have done your duty, I ſhall do mine,</hi> ſaid he, and ſo the Devil by his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, (to wit the falſe Prophet and the beaſt, who) caſt us into priſon, where we found the ſame unclean ſpirit, but could not bow to it, in ſubmitting to extortion, oppreſſion and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore were caſt into a ſtinking dungeon among thieves fellons and tranſgreſſors, dung, piſs, fleas and lice in abundance, and without ſtraw to lie upon; but <hi>the ſervant is not greater then his Lord, who had not where on to lay his head, though the foxes have holes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:33077:15"/>
                  <p>And let ſuch who fear the Lord conſider, if it be not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirit of the Devil which rules in theſe blind hired Prieſts, who take councel together in the darkneſs, with the beaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling, threatning, preaching againſt, and perſecuting even unto bonds, and impriſonments, whipping, ſtocking and ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thruſting into holes and dungeons, the innocent ſervants of the Lord, whoſe pure conſciences are exerciſed toward him, &amp; in love to all people for the ſeeds ſake for wch they ſuffer all things, <hi>and love not their lives unto the death, who follow the Lamb, the Light of the World,</hi> in this mighty day of battel between the two ſeeds, and let all ſuch who love Truth, and honeſtly deſire to come to the knowledge thereof, in the inward parts, (for that which may be known of God is manifeſt within, the people may feel alter him and finde him, who ſaves from ſin, and reconciles to God in the Light;) Conſider I ſay we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever any of the holy men of God, Chriſt his Apoſtles, or Miniſters did perſecute, rule, threaten or murther the innocent in them, or caſt any into priſon, (as <hi>Robert Dingley</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Bowrman</hi> hath done;) but on the contrary ſuffered under ſuch an evil adulterous gainſaying and perſecuting generation <hi>(the ſeed of the Serpent)</hi> even as the ſervants of the moſt high, his Children of Light have, and doth grievouſly ſuffer at this day, for bearing teſtimony for the Lord, and againſt the beaſt and falſe Prophet, wicked Rulers, Prieſts and People without reſpect of perſons, who with their cruel tyranny and oppreſſion <hi>ſmite the guiltles with the fiſt of wickedneſs</hi> to uphold the Devils dark Dominion, and <hi>Babylons Marchants,</hi> the unclean Hireling Prieſts, Sermons and Prayer-ſellers, who (raven like Wolves, &amp;) have wearied the Lord of hoſts with their words, <hi>ſpeaking peace to the wicked who put into their mouths,</hi> and ſuch who dare not for Conſcience ſake, <hi>they prepare war in their hearts,</hi> and caſt them into priſons where ſundry have ſuffered until death, <note n="*" place="margin">Read a Book ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled a <hi>Record of ſufferings for tythes.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>a testimony againſt them for ever,</hi> who have robbed, ſpoyld and made a Prey of mens goods, ſo that the Scripture is fulfilled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heads which ſaid <hi>Hoſea 6. 9. as troopes of robbers wait for a man, ſo a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Prieſts murther in the way by conſent,</hi> ſee <hi>Micha</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33077:15"/> 23. Ezek. 34. Eſa. 56. <hi>Math.</hi> 23. So that the holy men of God, Chriſt and his Apoſtles and Miniſters did witneſſe, and pronounced woes againſt ſuch, who did profeſs and preach the good words, who were ſtrangers, and perſecuted the life (from whence the good word came forth freely) even as <hi>Robert Dingley, Thomas Bowrman</hi> and the reſt of their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do, and have done, who walk in the very foot ſteps of <hi>the Scribes and Phariſees, and of the falſe Prophets in Cain, Cores and Balaams</hi> way, <hi>Curſed Children, that cannot ceaſe from ſin, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 14. Let ſuch who deſire to fear the Lord our God, be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the eternal witneſs the Light of Chriſt in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and with a ſingle eye ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee if it be not even ſo. Thus far have I cleard my Conſcience, for the ſimples ſake, as a teſtimony againſt the ſeed of evil doers, by whom I ſuffer, with the reſt of my Brethren, by them known <hi>in that which is hid from the eyes which are full of Adultery, and cannot ceaſe from ſin,</hi> and to ſuch my fleſh is known by the name of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Daniel Baker.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Wincheſter Bridewel</hi> 
                        <date>this 2. of the 6. <hi>Moneth</hi> 58.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>BY what was laſt written it may appear, who was in the Truth, he that was willing to have all things proved and brought to the Light, in publick before the people, in ſoberneſs and plaineſs, or Prieſt <hi>Dingly,</hi> who unto a reaſonable offer, did not give a reaſonable, but an unreaſonable anſwer, ſaying, <hi>I ſhall ſend thee to Priſon,</hi> and then whether he was in the Truth that did caſt into Priſon, without any offence, or he that was impriſoned, And moreover the fruits of their faſts doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, who live in pride, envy, and coveteouſneſs) in haling two of the Servants of Chriſt the ſame day out of their Synagague and before a Magiſtrate, and caſt them into priſon, and ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the Scripture, <hi>not knowing the Father nor the Son, John</hi> 16. 2. 3. and ſo it's plain, <hi>their dayes of fasting is for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, and ſuch God heareth not, for they are according to their fathers of old,</hi> Eſa. 58.</p>
            <p>Again thoſe Prieſts in the dayes of the King, did keep dayes of faſting and praying for their King, but was not their mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33077:16"/> in their hearts, and their ſacrifice like <hi>Cains,</hi> for did not they ſtir up the people to riſe, and if poſſible cut off all them that then ſought for Truth and liberty, and do not the ſame Prieſts now, even upon their dayes of humiliation, ſtir up the people againſt us they then called <hi>Round heads,</hi> and now called <hi>Quakers?</hi> if poſſible to have us all cut off, from being a people among them, to bear witneſs againſt their tyranny and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and <hi>John Hodder</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Haychurch</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> (whoſe moſt bloody perſecution againſt me and others have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded many;) he ſaid <hi>if his Lord Protector would raiſe an Army to cut off all the</hi> Quakers, <hi>he would be the firſt man that would draw the ſword;</hi> Oh! when did ever any man thirſt more for blood? and are not the Prieſts always ſtiring up ſtrife, and did not they ſtill pray for the upholding of that which they ſaw was going down, and that which indeed the Lord was overturning, looke back and ſee what an out-cry there was amongſt them, for their Fathers the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and for their King; and ſee if God did not overturn thoſe that they prayed for, and ſet up thoſe that they prayed againſt as Hereticks, and Rebels to their King, and breakers of their Laws, and ſee whether they that prayed for the King, and for the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> do not now pray for their Protector, [who with others was inſtrumental for the overturning of their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and their King, the hand of God being then with him;] who now hath turned his hand for the Prieſts, whom God is againſt, and hath made a Law for them, far exeeding any that was made for them, by any King or Queen; and therefore now, they boaſt much of their <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> and pray for him, as they did for their <hi>King,</hi> and he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them dayes to faſt and pray with and for him, as their <hi>King</hi> did, and this is their <hi>Protector,</hi> who protecteth them, by whom hundreds of us do ſuffer, who fought with him againſt them, their <hi>Biſhops</hi> and their <hi>Kings;</hi> but certainly the Lord God will turn both them and their prayers backward, therefore let the Protector take heed, how he ſet theſe treacherous, changeable, curſed Children, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 14. To pray for him, or with him, in his faſting dayes, or otherwiſe, for the ſame ſpirit in them which did pray for their Kings, doth now pray for their <hi>Protector,</hi> and the Lord is as much and more againſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33077:16"/> them now, then he was in the dayes of their <hi>Kings,</hi> and all that joyn with them, or upholds them, for he changeth not, though they do; therefore I, who was alway and am a friend to the juſt liberty of the Nation, do deſire all Magiſtrates to take heed of theſe Prieſts, leaſt they by their fallaſies and flatteries, exalt them in that which God is againſt, until his wrath break forth againſt them all together: for reaſonable men may almoſt ſee, that they are not like to ſtand long, there is ſuch a ſtir and a cry among them, and ſo much praying and crying dayly for the upholding of their trade, for ſuch a noiſe there was, with long and lowd Hypocritical Prayers, a little before, and at the very time that their <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> were overtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ever, and the Prieſts or Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the groves, they were many of them, and they alſo had dayes ſet apart to offer ſacrifice, and they prayed long, and cryed aloud, but none heard nor anſwered, and this was a little before they alſo were deſtroyed forever.</p>
            <p>But to return to this Prieſt <hi>Dingly</hi> in particular, after the Servants of God a fore named bad been kickt, beaten with a ſtaff, <hi>and fiſts of wickedneſs,</hi> upon his faſting day, and had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to be impriſoned (by the help of <hi>Thomas Bowrman)</hi> then from the priſon did they write unto him, who was ſo bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, like the Paſtors before, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 21. That he would not read the Letter, nor open it, but in a filthy fottiſh manner took a payer of tongs, and held it to a Candle, and burnt it, ſaying, <hi>he would try whether it were bewitched, or the Devil in it;</hi> but he himſelfe is in the witchcraft, not obeying the Truth, as may eaſily be proved, <hi>Gal</hi> 3. And envy which is of the Devil is found in himſelfe, the which Spirit of the Devil that guided him therein, would alſo burn their bodies that ſent it, if he had but a Law, and ſuch a power as his fathers the <hi>Biſhops</hi> had, who burnt the Martyrs; and he alſo then ſaid, <hi>the Devil is in you;</hi> but people may ſee, there is ſomething of God in us, guiding us in patience to undergo much ſufferings, and <hi>all manner of evil, that is done, or ſpoken againſt us, for his names ſake who is in us</hi> which to us turns for a teſtimony, againſt the world that we are of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 12. 13. And it is becauſe of the Spirit of Chriſt in us, (which teſtifies againſt the world, that we are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33077:17"/> and that Spirit of Chriſt in us is, that which Prieſt <hi>Dingly</hi> call eth a <hi>Devil,</hi> ſaying, <hi>the Devil is in you,</hi> but it being <hi>Chriſt in us the hope of glory,</hi> he is an open Blaſpemer, and a denyer of Chriſt, that is come in the fleſh, and ſo he is an Antichriſt; Therefore all are to beware of hearkning to his Doctrine, being found a Blaſpemer, though he may ſpeak never ſo ſmooth words, for he is not only full of envy, but alſo of conveteouſneſs, for he claimed 3 <hi>l.</hi> (or leſs) for tythes of <hi>John Dayes,</hi> who deſired not his Miniſtery, and then inſtead of leſs then 3 <hi>l.</hi> he cauſed four cows to be taken from him worth above 12 <hi>l.</hi> and ſo he is not only <hi>in filthy Lucre</hi> (contrary to the Scripture) <hi>whoſe mouth ſhould be ſtopt,</hi> but alſo unreaſonable therein, to demand 3 <hi>l.</hi> of a man that owed him nothing, and then to have above four times ſo much as he ask't for, taken from him, <hi>Hoſea</hi> might well number ſuch as he amongſt <hi>Robbers and Murtheres, Hoſea</hi> 6. 9. and this is not all neither, for after he had cauſed theſe 4 cowes to be taken from him, he alſo cauſed the man himſelfe to be caſt into priſon, becauſe he came into his own Pariſh Steeple-houſe, and ſpoke ſome words there, and as for coming into the Steeple-houſe, he had as much right as another man of their Pariſh; and ſometimes the Prieſts and Rulers would force friends to pay <hi>2s 6d.</hi> becauſe they do not come to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſteeple-houſe, and when they do come, they ſend them to priſon for coming, was ever the like wickedneſs practiſed by any Prieſts and Rulers before? And in all theſe things, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Bowrman</hi> was a Servant to the corrupt coveteous will of this perſecuting Prieſt, for by his order alſo or warrant, was <hi>John Dayes</hi> cowes taken away, and he himſelfe ſent to priſon, where he is now committed to the houſe of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>And moreover <hi>R. D.</hi> did cauſe <hi>Winifred Newman</hi> to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for ſpeaking a few words in his <hi>Steeple-houſe,</hi> after he had done, and ſhe was a ſervant to a Widow, and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and from them the Prieſt cauſed her to be taken to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſuch as he <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cryed againſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 10, 11. for in his dayes alſo <hi>widowes became their prey, and they robbed the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe,</hi> Iſa. 10. 2. And what an unreaſonable thing was this, to rob the <hi>Fatherleſſe and Widow of a ſervant,</hi> who was daily
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33077:17"/> ſerviceable unto them; but now they commit iniquity by their Law, but the Law of God is made for men-ſtealers, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10. And <hi>T. B.</hi> ſent her to Priſon alſo, and ſo conſented with the Thief, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 18. and was in all theſe things a ready ſervant to this ungodly Prieſt, whom at preſent I leave untill the hand of God overturn him, and all the reſt, that they may leave their names for a hiſſing and a curſe, like the Biſhops before them, who were as loath to come down, as the Prieſts are to follow after.</p>
            <p rend="italic">Here followeth ſomething in ſhort of the long unjuſt impriſonment of <hi>James Pottar,</hi> being alſo a husbandman, taken out of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt employment by the means of the Prieſt of the Pariſh of <hi>Baghuſt,</hi> whoſe name is <hi>Edward Bental.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
               <body>
                  <p>I Who am clear in the fight of God of the breach of any law either of God, or of the Nation, by which I may juſtly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or of any evill intent or purpoſe againſt the perſon of any man or woman whatſoever, but have and do deſire <hi>to keepe a conſcience void of offence towards God and man;</hi> as the Lord of life, whom I ſerve in my ſpirit knoweth; yet was I by order from <hi>Richard Kingſmill,</hi> and <hi>William Withar,</hi> who are ſet to do juſtice in the County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> taken out of my honeſt lawfull employments, without any examination, not having that liberty as to appear before them to anſwer for my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe falſe accuſations (which through envy, and from the wickedneſſe of the hearts of <hi>Edward Bentall</hi> Prieſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) was laid to my charge, but was had away to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Gaol at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> where I was kept a cloſe Priſoner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Affizes following, at which time I was had up to the Bar amongſt Thieves and Murtherers: And although nothing of what I was accuſed, nor any evill was there proved againſt me, yet was I by the Order of Judge <hi>Nicholas</hi> returned back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the Gaol, there to be kept a Priſoner, unleſſe I would pay a fine of five pounds, becauſe I did not put off my hat, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Heatheniſh cuſtome, which there is no law in the Nation for: And as for the Law of God, he that reſpecteth perſons, or preferreth him that weareth the gay cloathing &amp; gold
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33077:18"/> Ring, before him that is in vile rayment, maketh himſelfe a tranſgreſſor.</p>
                  <p>Now thus I declare, that I owe no man any thing but love, yet am I ordered to continue in Priſon (untill I pay the ſaid fine of 5 <hi>l.</hi>) where I have been already kept before, and ſince the aforeſaid Aſſize, about 63 weeks amongſt Thieves &amp; Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, Drunkards, Swearers, Blaſphemers, and almoſt all manner of wicked perſons; by whoſe wickedneſſe and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practices my ſoule hath been daily grieved, and my life of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten burthened, and preſſed down, yea what I have in this place ſuffered is not herein to be named; but woe unto them by whom the occaſion cometh, by which the juſt doth ſuffer.</p>
                  <p>Thus I who am free-born of the Nation, am not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of my right and liberty in the Nation (which hath been ſo much contended about, and ſo much blood ſhed for) but alſo kept in long and cruell bondage (contrary to any Law ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God or man) by moſt unjuſt and unreaſonable men, and that not for any evil, or with-holding from any man his right, or the honour that is due to any, who do honour all men in the Lord, though the worlds honour, with all their cuſtomes, faſhions and traditions I deny for ever; but if humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be before honour, as the Scripture doth witneſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 13 <hi>and</hi> 18, 12. then a proud man is not to be honoured, and he that honoreth the proud (whom the Lord reſiſts) he honoreth the Devil, who is king over all the children of pride, <hi>Job</hi> 41. 34. who is their head and ruleth in them, and ſo the honour which proud fleſh doth love, and luſt after, who are angry and ſeek revenge by caſting into priſon, or otherwiſe perſecuting where its not given them, is to be denyed by all them that fear the Lord, and this I know that thoſe that witneſs the fleſh cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, <hi>with the affections and luſts,</hi> they cannot feed nor ſatisfie the luſts in others where it ruleth, by giving them honour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their corrupt wills, though they ſuffer by them, as I do (at this day) under their mercileſſe cruelty and tyranny.</p>
                  <p>Oh! how hath the Devill blinded the minds of people, who are ſo fooliſh, vain, and corrupt in their carriages one towards another, with bowing, bending, cringing, putting off hats, with fooliſh geſtures and deceitfull words, as <hi>Your humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33077:18"/> and ſuch like, being proud, haughty, &amp; high-minded, and will ſcoffe, and mock, deſpiſe one another when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and ſeek one anothers hurt, when anger ariſeth in them one againſt another. And at the Aſſizes will not Thieves and Murtherers put off their hats to the Judge, and give him the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile of <hi>your Honour?</hi> and call him their Lord, and down upon their knees to him, as at the aforeſaid Affizes? And wherefore is it? to honour him, when as perhaps, if ſo be they had him in another place with opportunity, they would make him bow to them, and take away his money, if not his life.</p>
                  <p>What curſed flattery and deceit is uſed among people who know not God, <hi>nor feare before him?</hi> and how is proud fleſh bewitched with it? How common is it for the poor man to ſtand uncovered to the rich? giving deceitfull Titles, as <hi>Your Worſhip, your Honour,</hi> and ſuch like, whereby <hi>God is robbed, to whom all honour, glory, and worſhip is to be given:</hi> and he that is rich and great in the earth, giving the plain language of <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> (and is not here reſpect of perſons, by which the law of God is tranſgreſſed?) And when the poor man is gone from the rich, he will ſpeak plainly of him, and ſay he is proud, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, and the like, and this I have often ſeen and heard, and aske them wherefore they uſe ſuch deceit in their carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them? they will many of them acknowledge and ſay, they muſt do it, the great men look for it, and their cauſes elſe they will not heare, nor do any thing for them; and this deceit and flattery is of the Devill, and ſo the Devill in them is pleaſed with it; but ſuch who cannot bow to his pride, but ſtand witneſſes againſt it (who can bow to none but the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone) ſuch he perſecutes and caſts into priſon.</p>
                  <p>He that boweth to the will of man, to pleaſe or have the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of proud fleſh, he is an idolater, and a tranſgreſſor of the Law, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down nor worſhip any,</hi> and ſuch bow not to the Son of God, <hi>to whom every knee ſhall bow;</hi> and ſuch who call themſelves Chriſtians, and are ſeeking their own honour, are hypocrites, mockers, and diffemblers with God, the Son of God, who came to do the will of his Father, and did the works that none could do beſides, ſaid, <hi>I receive not honour from man,</hi> John 5. 41. And ſaid to ſuch who were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33077:19"/> ſeeking their own honour, <hi>how can ye believe which receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God only,</hi> John 5. 44. And ſo ſuch who are ſeeking and receiving <hi>honour one of another,</hi> are not believers, nor come to the faith, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects no mans perſon, and ſo are <hi>Infidels, and without God in the world.</hi> And theſe are they that would have the ſervants of God how dovvn, and become ſervants to their corrupt wills, <hi>who know not God, neither are of him,</hi> but are enemies to him in all their ways, and are of the generation fo proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who <hi>Mordecai</hi> refuſed to bow unto, although it was the command of the King; and therefore did <hi>Haman</hi> build a Gallows fifty cubits high to hang him thereon, <hi>Eſther</hi> 7. 9. And alſo did ſeek to deſtroy all the <hi>Jewes</hi> that were in the Kings Provinces; and the ſame ſpirit is it that now ruleth in all ſuch who perſecute the ſervants of God, by caſting them into priſon, where their wills is not obeyed, nor bowed unto, by giving the honour of the world unto them.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore all people minde the light of Chriſt in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that reproveth for ſin and evill, and of all your pride, deceit, hypocriſie, and reſpecting of perſons, and of all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, that by it you may be lead out of the world, and out of all its wayes, faſhions, cuſtomes, and traditions, which are evill, up unto God, to ſerve and worſhip him alone, who is a jealous God, <hi>and will not give his glory unto another, who will bring down the mighty from their ungodly ſeats, and will exalt the meeke and the lowly,</hi> and all that are proud and do wickedly and all that perſecute and make a prey upon the innocent, ſhall be as the chaffe before an unquencheable fire; <hi>And the loftineſſe of man ſhall be bowed downe, and his haughtineſſe laid low, in this the day of his mighty power, in which he is ariſing to ſhake terribly the earth, &amp; to give unto myſtery</hi> Babylon <hi>and all her Merchants that are trading with her the cup of the wine of the fierceneſs of his wrath, and all who worſhip the Beaſt or his Image, and are joyned together with him (making war againſt the Lamb and his followers) ſhall have their portion together in the Lake that burns for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>James Pottar.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33077:19"/>
            <p rend="italic">Having thus let the cauſe appear of the committing of other friends under their own hands, and having not been wanting before in ſending &amp; writing unto the Rulers, to lay their unjuſt retaining of us in bo nds before them thereby to attain our juſt liberty; but being moſt like at preſent to be deprived thereof, &amp; ſeeing that they commit more alſo unto Priſon, we willingly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether gave up our bodies to ſuffer, if it were untill death, and onely ſought to have the liberty to worke as before was mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; therefore we writ as followeth, and ſent it to them called Juſtice <hi>Cobb,</hi> and Juſtice <hi>Betſworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
               <body>
                  <p>WE whoſe conſciences are clear in the ſight of the living God, that we have not injured nor wronged any perſon, neither broke the Law of God, whoſe witneſs will abide in us for ever, that we are this day in bonds for the teſtimony of a <hi>a good conſcience,</hi> under the cruel oppreſſion of men of ſin, who have taken ſeveral of us out of our honeſt lawful employments, and in priſon kept us from our labours, which we ſhould labour in, for the maintenance of our ſelves and families, whoſe ſouls do abhor idleneſs, neither dare we eat any mans bread for nought; and by this unjuſt impriſonment have many of us ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much, becauſe we could not proceed in our preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſome of our families alſo wanting us much, whoſe wives are left as Widows, and children as the fatherleſs: And ſeeing mens hearts continue ſo hard, as to keep us ſo long in bonds from our buſineſſe, therefore we have endeavoured to have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to work with our hands in the Priſon, ſomething where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of having been granted by order in writing from <hi>John Bulkley.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We being in all 7 perſons kept always cloſe priſoners, and what abuſes and hard-ſhips we have ſuffered, we mention lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle herein, who are not only deprived of our way of livelyhood and liberty in the Nation, but alſo reſtrained from having that liberty which the reſt of the ſervants of God have in moſt, or in all Priſons in <hi>England,</hi> which is, of having liberty for one or more of us to go forth into the Town to buy food, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide other neceſſaries for the reſt; and for want of this liberty we have often wanted water to drink, and ſometimes bread to eat, and other things when ſome of us have been ſick, yet have we not troubled you with many complaints herein, but in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33077:20"/> have we powred forth our ſouls with prayers and tears un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord God of life, who ſeeth all our wants, and knoweth our innocency, and in his due time can us deliver; but if not, to the Devill we cannot bow, for <hi>our ſoules are ſubject to the higher power,</hi> which preſerved them that broke the decrees and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of men, which is more then is juſtly charged upon us, <hi>Eſther.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 17, 18.</p>
                  <p>Now the thing which we write for, is that which is juſt in the ſight of God, and but reaſonable in the ſight of any reaſonable Miniſter of the Law (which law they themſelves ſay ſhould be grounded upon reaſon) which thing is, we being ſix men, and one woman, that ſhe the aforeſaid woman, whoſe name is <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifred Newman,</hi> or any other of us, may have liberty to go forth and buy, &amp; bring in other needful things for the reſt of us, that ſo we may no more be put to the extreamity of want, nor to the charge of hiring another to do that for us, which we might well do our ſelves, who have been at great charge already, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other loſſe, and that ſhe or another of us may alſo bring work in and out for us, and ſuch things as may be needfull for us to work with and upon; And that ſhe, or either of us, having this liberty granted, ſhal be as a priſoner, without the leaſt intent of running away, we ſhall all engage and promiſe, ſo far as men fearing God can promiſe herein, that which we chiefly intend is combing of Wool.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>A ſpeedy anſwer or order in writing herein is expected, &amp; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to juſtice deſired by the members of Chriſt in Priſon (&amp; houſe of Correction) at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> whoſe names are Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Melledg, William Baily, Humphrey Smith, James Pottar, Daniel Baker, George Henderſon,<hi> and </hi>Winifred Newman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>THis Paper was directed and ſent to Juſtice</hi> Cobb, <hi>and Juſtice</hi> Betſworth <hi>(as they were called) but was chiefly intended for Justice</hi> Cobb, <hi>who was as Judge at the Seſſions before, who being without naturall affection, denyed the members of Chriſt in priſon this ſo reaſonable a thing, the which then I laid before the under-Sheriffe, and read a Copie of the Paper to him, he being then in the Priſon, who granted the thing to be but reaſonable, whereby it doth appeare, that he and them that ſhould do Juſtice were unreaſonable, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which was reaſonable, and he ſaid as the Juſtices did, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33077:20"/> it was not in his power, then I asked him, in whoſe power it was, to grant this reaſonable thing, ſeeing both Juſtices Sherif and Goaler had denyed it, then he referred me to one</hi> Browning, <hi>but ſuddenly I was informed that he was a Papist, and ſo I laid the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it upon him, that we (of whom ſome had been Captains, and others long ſerviceable for liberty from under Popiſh Tyranny, ſhould be now deprived of all Juſtice and Equity and referred only to the the mercy of a Popiſh man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh the cruelty and hard heartedneſs of the Sons of men, who can read it without mourning, no Transgreſſor in the priſon but might be heard, nor the cauſe of any thief ſo turned aſide, but the Lord of mercy was our refuge, who is a preſent help in time of need, and can never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get his Covenant, nor for ſake his afflicted, who abide faithfull, who in his mercy preſerveth his Servants, but overturneth his enemies, for ever, and be did viſit for theſe things, and began to avenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on his adverſaries, though his Lambs rejoyceth not when the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies falleth, nor in that the Devils are made ſubject, but in that there names are written among the living, but in our affliction I writ the a foregoing paper, and ſent it to Juſtice</hi> Cob <hi>and</hi> Betſworth, <hi>upon the</hi> 11. <hi>day of the</hi> 4. <hi>moneth the</hi> 6. <hi>day of the week, and upon the</hi> 16. <hi>day of the ſame moneth the</hi> 4. <hi>day of the week at night the a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Juſtice</hi> Cob <hi>was ſuddenly cut off, though no outward eye ſaw how, wch was to the aſtoniſhment of his family and many more And the man which the Juſtice and Prieſt</hi> Bental <hi>cauſed to ſwear falſly againſt</hi> James Pottar, <hi>the ſame man was ſince that time bruiſed, torn, and ſpoyled with a horſe and harrows, ſo that he died very ſhortly after being before troubled in conſcience for what he had ſworn; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Scripture is fulfilled, when the Lords hand is lifted up, they will not ſee but they ſhall ſee and be aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it may be obſerved that we had ſent ſeveral other papers to the Justice</hi> Cob <hi>(ſome whereof are herein written) all which he little regarded, he being a great enemy to Truth, and a Perſecutor of friends, he being as a judge at another ſeſſions was not ſatisfied, with the committing of</hi> Stephen Bevis <hi>to the houſe of correction, (who was before committed by</hi> Col. Norton, <hi>to the common Goal for hearing teſtimony against Prieſt</hi> Simons <hi>falſe Doctrine) but alſo gave order that he ſhould not be ſuffered to work at his trade, but be put to pounding of hemp or ſome harder work though he declared his willingneſs in open court to work at his trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
               <body>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:33077:21"/>
                  <head>A Copy of a paper to the ſeſſions.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>You at whoſe hands the dreadful God of life, and his Servants doth require right and ſound judgement, to be by you performed at this preſent ſeſſions at <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>LEt our ſeveral cauſes be heard and read in open court, and let our innocent ſufferings appear in the Light, before the eyes of the people, and let them by whom we ſuffer be made manifeſt, and do not ſhut up things in darkneſs, as at the laſt ſeſſions, not ſuffering the cauſe of them who are oppreſſed to be read in the open Court, wherein, and in many other things we have been deprived of that which is juſt and right, the wch i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> proceeded in, will even be a ſhame unto you, for juſtice, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and true Judgement is that we do both expect, and would gladly ſee brought forth in you; therefore do not wait to lay farther ſnares, to betray the ſimple, whereby to cover that oppreſsion ſome of you have acted in againſt the Servants of the living God, but let the fear of God guide you, that ſound Judgement you may come unto, whereby rightly to underſtand, what or what manner of evil, we have done, or what Law of God we have broken, and what accuſations are againſt us, with the ground and cauſe of thoſe accuſations, and take heed of entertaining falſe witneſs, or joyning with it, or forcing men to ſwear againſt the members of Chriſt, contrary to Gods witneſs in them, (as <hi>Thomas Bowrman</hi> hath done) and if any thing be, or hath been proved, or any one falſely accuſed, either of the Servants of God, or any other, you are to ſee that you do not puniſh ſuch accuſed above or beyond the fact, or crime charged againſt them, and herein all that rule for God, are and ſhould be guided with an underſtanding heart, in the ſpirit of wiſdom, and knowledge, as <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, Solomon</hi> and others were, that none may be oppreſſed by wrong Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor inſnared becauſe of envy, and prejudice which lodgeth in the deceitful hearts of men, who are out of Gods fear.</p>
                  <p>For we who are in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> do wait to have true Judgement ſet up in the earth, in righteouſneſs, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in and among the Sons of men, and are friends unto and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33077:21"/> Lovers of all them who judge for God, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and a praiſe to them that do well; And he that reproves a Hireling that ſtands praying in the Synagogue, doth well, for <hi>Eſaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Micah, Malachiah, Hoſea,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did reprove, and bear teſtimony againſt ſuch, and for the ſame things are the members of Chriſt, in your dayes <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of the Synagogues, brought before Rulers, and caſt into Priſon,</hi> whom you ſhould be a praiſe unto, for therein they do well, being moved of the Lord thereunto, whoſe mouthes, by men of ſin, are not to be ſtopped, though they would have us, or command us to ſpeak no more in his name who maketh an end of ſin, and ſaid I am the Light of the world, whoſe Light hath led us out of evil, and ſo are become a prey unto an adulterous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that know not God, whoſe love in our hearts, hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained us to obey him rather then man, in that wherein man would hinder us in our obedience unto God, whoſe power worketh in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s mightily, which keepeth us from under the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of mans corrupt will, yet to the higher power our ſouls are ſubject, even to that power which preſerved them who broke the Commands and Decrees of men, <hi>Heſt. 3. 2. Dan. 3. Dan. 6 Acts 4. 17. 18.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Several papers have we ſent to you (who ſhould do Juſtice) of our unjuſt and unreaſonable ſufferings in priſon, and little hath it been by you regarded, one of which papers we ſent by a friend to <hi>John Hook</hi> (called a Juſtice) of <hi>Bramſhot,</hi> which friend, ſince gave us an account in writing, that when he came to deliver the paper, <hi>John Hooks</hi> Clerk beat him in the houſe, and others alſo abuſed him and, after he was gone out of the houſe, another who belonged to the houſe followed him, and in a Lane did beat him, and kick him very much, and this was very evil, which you are to puniſh.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Here followeth a ſhort Relation of ſomething of the cauſe of the committing and retaining of the members of Chriſt in priſon.</head>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Anthony Melledg</item>
                              <item>William Baily</item>
                              <item>Humphrey Smith</item>
                           </list> 
                           <hi>IMpriſoned two weeks without the breach of any Law, and ſince kept in the Houſe of Correction about 17 weeks from their buſineſs, and from their home, becauſe they cannot promiſe to go home, who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33077:22"/>know no law requiring them to make any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and</hi> where there is no law, there is no tranſgreſſion.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>Winif. Newman <hi>Impriſoned for ſpeaking a few ſober words to the hireling Prieſt</hi> (who cannot ceaſe from ſin, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 14.) <hi>after he had ended, ſhe being before a ſervant to a Widow and fatherleſs, and ſo the hireling Prieſt by cauſing her to be impriſoned, hath cauſed both ſhe, the widow and the fatherleſſe to ſuffer.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <list>
                              <item>Daniel Baker</item>
                              <item>Geo: Henderſon</item>
                           </list> 
                           <hi>Impriſoned for ſpeaking words of truth to the ſame Prieſt and people, which Priest ſaid,</hi> that God was author of evill. <hi>And another Prieſt before the Magiſtrate wreſted the Scripture, to affirm,</hi> that Chriſt did ſwear, <hi>when he ſaid,</hi> Verily, verily.</p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>John Day <hi>Impriſoned for reproving the ſame hireling Prieſt</hi> (Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Dingly) <hi>who confeſt</hi> he and his flock were full of ſin and evill, <hi>which alſo doth appear by their envy and perſecution, which is of the Devill.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>James Pottar <hi>Impriſoned without the breach of any law, and fined at the following Aſſizes 5 l. becauſe he could not tranſgreſſe the Law of God, by reſpecting of perſons, to ſatisfie the luſts and corrupt wills of men, in not putting off his hat when he was brought to the ſaid Aſſizes, of whom alſo is demanded 3 l. for fees, who have been kept a cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner under theſe cruell oppreſſions 59 weeks and ſome dayes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>From them who are not onely ready to ſuffer bonds, and long unjuſt impriſonments, but alſo death it ſelf, if the Lord require it of us, in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt all Deceivers, and all manner of unrighteouſneſſe and oppreſſions; and we are friends to the Common-wealth, and to equity and true judgement, having true love to the ſouls of all mankinde, who for the teſtimony of a pure conſcience are Priſoners by the corrupt wills of men, in the Common Gaol and houſe of Correction at</hi> Winton.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At this last Seſſions</hi> D. B. G. H. I. D. <hi>were committed to the Houſe of Correction (being priſoners before) the which them ſet to do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice would not have done, if they had not looked out more at the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous hireling Prieſts vain customes, and the glory of the world, which ſhall all periſh, then to the light of Chriſt (which endureth for ever) in their conſciences which did then much judge them for what they did againſt the ſervants of God, and let them ſee their evill therein, the which Light they are to love, obey, and follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33077:22"/>
                        <head>From the ſervant of God in Priſon to the Judge of the Aſſize at <hi>Wincheſter. A Copie of a Paper to the Aſſizes.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe righteous Judge of heaven and earth, who reſpecteth not the perſons of the mighty, who tryeth the hearts of Kings, who is the mighty God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and their ſeed (who wandred up and down) ſome having <hi>no certain dwelling place,</hi> even he who ſeeth the ſecret intents of the hearts of the ſons of men, whoſe judgements are juſt and true, <hi>who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth the proud in his judgements, and heareth the cry of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> who will reprove Kings for the ſake of the ſimple, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh not his faithfull afflicted ones, who by the man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will judge the ſecrets of all mens hearts, according to his light in them, whereby every man ſhall receive a juſt recompence of reward, according to all their words and actions, whether for, or againſt him and his people.</p>
                        <p>Wherefore this O man! thou art to know, that true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ight and ſound judgement is to be by thee performed, according to the righteous Law of God, which is written in the heart, that corrupt judgement, cruelty, perſecution, nor receiving of gifts, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining falſe witneſs, may not be found in thee, nor in any of them that Joine with thee, whether they are called Sheriffs, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Jury men, Clarks, or any other; but that according to the Law of God, in his fear thou may perform that which the Lord God of hoſts certainly will require of thee, in the day when all the arme of fleſh, and honour of the world will not prevent the true &amp; everlaſting judgments of the moſt high, with fierce wrath and indignation upon all them who pervert true judgment, and tranſgreſs the righteous Law of God written in the heart.</p>
                        <p>The which that thou may not do, nor ſee done before thine eys, when thou may prevent it, and that thou may eſcape the wrath of the Almighty, which will certainly come upon all who pervert judgment, and that in the councell of God thou may come to ſtand in meekneſſe and godly fear, <hi>to judge for God, &amp; not for man,</hi> that his will by thee may be performed; that when thou come to ſtand before the Throne of his eternal judgments, thou may not be turned to the left hand, with them that forget God, and turn his Law behind their backs, and oppreſs his ſervants, and neither viſit, relieve, nor ſet at liberty the members of Chriſt in Priſon,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33077:23"/> who in theſe your dayes are in moſt Priſons where thou come, and in Priſon have been ſick, and deprived of that liberty which Thieves and Murtherers have; &amp; that thou may come to be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Gods witneſs with it in thee, to ſee &amp; rightly to underſtand the ground and cauſe of things of which thou art to judge. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art thou to be guided by the light in thee, which comes from Chriſt, who is the ſure foundation, and was before-tranſgreſſion, by which the tranſgreſſion is ſeen, and with it is to be judged, which light in thee will let thee ſee the ground of all tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; by the ſame out of <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> thou art to be led, and then to judge over that which is in the <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> that ſo thoſe who dare not tranſgreſs the righteous law of God, thou mayſt be a praiſe unto, and all ſuch who reprove ſin in the gate, market pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, publick aſſemblies, or elſ-where; and that all who tranſgreſs the law of God, with that of God in thy conſcience, thou may be a terrour unto, executing true judgment upon that head wch goeth forth from the light, into the tranſgreſſion, for that is it for which the Law is added, which by the Law which is perfect is to be judged, that out of the tranſgreſſion man may be kept.</p>
                        <p>Therefore hear with meekneſs and in patience, underſtand and conſider my words; for all the holy men of God, who ruled for God, and not for men, were therein guided by that which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, pure, juſt and right, whereby they were guided in his fear, to execute his judgments only upon the tranſgreſſor, according to the will of him, by whom otherwiſe they themſelves were to be judged, and they were guided by that ſpirit in them which gave forth the Law, and with that joyned to execute the Law upon them that did tranſgreſs the law of God, with whom in ſo doing they were ſaid to be a help-government, and ſuch were called Gods, who bore not the ſword in vain, ſtanding in the higher power, to which their ſouls were ſubject, to bring the tranſgreſſor in obedience thereunto; but ſuch who did not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the righteous law of God, their ſouls were already ſubject to that <hi>higher power;</hi> but when man who ſhould rule for God, ſtood not in his councel, but went themſelves into the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (out of the power) and judged for reward, ſuch the light in them was darkned, that they could not ſee the tranſgreſſor, but let him go free, and puniſh the juſt, as <hi>Pilate</hi> and many others did, even in the dayes of the Prophets, who then cryed out againſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33077:23"/> them, becauſe they were become as ravening wolves, and then of ſuch it is written, <hi>I ſaid ye were gods, but ye ſhall dye like men, and fall as one of the Princes;</hi> and becauſe of wrong judgment, and the want of true exerciſe in the perfect law of God, have many fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and been overturned, even Kings, Princes, Parliaments, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Judges and Rulers, as alſo in theſe your days, even whole Nations turned up ſide down.</p>
                        <p>Therefore O man, let thy heart be opened to receive inſtruction from the Lord, and let thy mind be enlightned with the light of his Son, which light is it that giveth the knowledg of God, &amp; the right underſtanding of the perfect law of life, that in the light which comes from Chriſt, thy minde may be exerciſed towards God, that his enemies in his fear and dread thou may rule over, and unto the friends of Chriſt who do well, to be a praiſe, and a <hi>Miniſter of the law for good,</hi> that in thy place thou may be juſt, <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, and hating covetouſneſs, doing that which is good, that in the end of thy dayes thou may have the praiſe of the ſame, and receive that honour which man cannot keep from thee, that thy ſoul may reſt in peace,</hi> which is the deſire of the members of Chriſt in bonds at <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H. S.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="paper">
                     <body>
                        <head>A Copie of a warning to the Rulers.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>HEarken and hear ye men that ſhall dye, is it not for you O yee Judges, and Rulers of the earth, to know, believe in, and be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher power, even the eternall light of the Son of God in your conſciences, wherein true and ſound judgment is placed? thereby ſhould you be guided in the fear and councel of God to miniſter true &amp; ſound justice and judgment to all what ſoever Cauſes comes before you, with patience &amp; meekneſs to hear the poor, as well as the rich, for you are not to have reſpect of perſons in judgement, neither to take bribes, receive gifts or rewards, or receive, or give honour one to another, or compell any to give it to you, who ſeek and live not in the honour of God onely, your Judgement being corrupted, the eye being blinded by the God of the world, who with his ſubjects or ſervaats would be honoured,</hi> above all that is called God, <hi>and ſo the juſt ſuffers, the ſword is laid upon the innocent (the guiltleſs ſmitten with the fiſt of wickedneſſe) which ſword ſhould ſlay the tranſgreſſor. Take heed you be not ſuddenly destroyed by the hand of the great and mighty God, and ſo you bring eternall Iudgement and condemnation upon your heads; which moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly will be executed upon all that forget God, who ſhall be curſed from his preſence, and turned into hell.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33077:24"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wherefore know that there is no iniquity, neither repect of perſons with the Lord God of hoſts, who hath ſhaken his hand at diſhoneſt gain, and deſpiſeth the gain of oppreſſion, even he then will be with you in the Judgment, when as you to his power become ſubject, and ſo you will be a good ſavour to the upright in heart, &amp; anſwer that of God in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and</hi> becom a terror to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that do well, <hi>when you with a ſingle eye ſee, know, and lay the Sword in its due place, as men of truth,</hi> fearing God, hating covetouſneſs, <hi>meek and mercifull.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The mighty day of Gods wonderfull power (is come) and of your viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and time of tryall, (O ye rebellious Children of Darkneſs) who know not at what you stumble; yea, this day of the Lord is, and will be the life of all the meek of the earth, though it is &amp; will be a day of howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, trembling, and astoniſhment, of fury, blackneſs, &amp; darkneſs, and of eternall condemnation, to all the proud and lofty workers of iniquity, yea the day of breaking down, laying low the pride and loftineſs of men that ſhall dye is come, and the mighty God the Lord of hosts alone is, and ſhall be exalted.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wherefore woe from his dreadfull preſence to all the proud and lofty, and all that do wickedly, who are as ſtubble for the unquenchable fire, which is the portion of all that forget God, who put the day of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off, which is darkneſs &amp; not light unto ſuch who are ſtrong &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do evill, calling light darkneſs, and darkneſs light, turning judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment backward, laying the ſword (which ſhould be upon the head of the tranſgreſſor) upon the innocent, whoſe pure conſciences are exerciſed towards God; ſo that truth cannot enter, equity is fallen in the ſtreets, juſtice ſtandeth afar off, and as it was in the dayes of old, ſo it is now, He that departeth from iniquity, makes himſelf a prey, becomes a ſigne and a wonder to this evil, rebellious, &amp; adulterous generation: And thus the guiltleſs is ſmitten with the fist of wickedneſs, and the tranſgreſſor goes free, but he in whoſe ſight all the Nations are but as the drop of a bucket, whoſe name is dreadful among the heathen, even he is riſen to plead the cauſe of the innocent, confound, overturn, and break in pieces</hi> (as a potters veſſel) <hi>his enemies, with an utter overthrow, to ſet his poore priſoners and captivated ſuffering ſeed at liberty from ſuch who oppreſs perſecute, ſcorn, and make a prey, and puff at them. Woe be to you by whom we ſuffer.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wherefore this is a warning from a true Lover of your ſouls to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you, (O ye Judges and Rulers, for this County of Hampſhire)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33077:24"/> to repent and let this day of Gods love, and of your viſitation, be precious' in your ſight, who ſit in darkneſs under the ſhadow of death, and let this my Councel (in the fear of the Lord) be acceptable, and break off your mighty ſins by righteouſneſs, do justly, love mercy, relieve the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and let fruits meet for repentance be brought forth, therefore I ſay repent, and turn to the Lord God who is Light, a meaſure of which is in every of your Conſciences, a free gift the grace of God which is to (and will) lead to the God of the Spiris of all fleſh, as to it you become obedient, I ſay again let fruits meet for repentance be brought forth, least you be cut down as fruitles trees, and dye in your ſins.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wo be to you who are found among the unprofitable Servants perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting and making a prey upon the innocent, who are faithful witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the Lord God of life (which made the world) againſt all curſed practiſes and deeds of darkneſs whether in Priests, Rulers or People without reſpect of Perſons.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Remember you are warned in your life time, and ſo far he hath cleared his Conſcience in the fight of God (whether you hear or forbear) who am a Friend to that which exalts a Nation, a Lover of Soules, a Sufferer for the Teſtimony of a pure Conſcience, known to the World by the name of his fleſh,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Daniel Baker.</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Winchester</hi> Priſon <date>this 13. of the 5. moneth 58.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>Now this may be obſerved, that no Wanderer, nor Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor was kept in this priſon, nor houſe of correction becauſe they would not promiſe to go home, but only we who do not tranſgreſſe, and many perſons hath been committed to the houſe of correction ſince we, and ſoon releaſed again, as them <hi>Iriſh</hi> wandring men, who had not any habitation in <hi>England</hi> as we heare of, were ſoon releaſed, but not us, and again any of their complaints would be heard by the Rulers, and their papers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and read (which was but juſt) but why then ſhould we be deprived, of that right (every way) which they have, let the Rulers of <hi>Hampſhire</hi> return me any good reaſon according to Law, for their partiallity herein, for we ſent a copy of one of the papers before written, for ſome juſt right and liberty to <hi>John Bulkley</hi> (and a book which I freely gave him in which was ſome of his own actions which his Clerk ſaid his Maſter deſired it might be printed, and if ſo, he might as well deſire to have it) and he ſent his Clark after the meſſengers, who laid his hands on their goods, and broke up and read Letters which were of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33077:25"/> concernment, and he alſo took away from them, 7. or 8 books or there abouts, which books were as properly the Goods of us cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers,</hi> as the clothes on our backs, the which to be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently taken from us, is by us eſteemed no leſs then robbery, being not reſtored, and ſo to be puniſhed, and not practiſed by a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, eſpecially by ſuch a zealous out ſide profeſſor as <hi>John Bulkley.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo though any vile perſon might be heard, yet I have made it appear (but it is to the ſhame of the Rulers) that we ſent a meſſenger to <hi>John Hook</hi> of <hi>Bramſhot,</hi> and his Clark beat the Meſſenger, and we ſent another paper by other friends to <hi>John Bulkley,</hi> and did not he ſend his Clark and rob them? and then we ſent another paper, to that preverſe raſh tyrannical man, who is an evil example to all Rulers and People, called <hi>Iudge Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> at the Aſſiſes, and he bid the Goaler take that Meſſenger; Therefore now let Gods witneſs in every Conſcience anſwer, whether that which Rules in theſe (and the like) men be to be honoured, and they flattered or owned, to be men ruling for God, or to be herein denyed and declared againſt by all ſuch whoſe Soules are ſubject to the higher power, which is Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, which whoſoever reſiſts, to pleaſe ſuch mens wills, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> (of darkneſs) kept the Servants of God in bondadge, and would not let them go, for which the plagues and Judgements of God came upon him, and at laſt thick darkneſs which might be felt, and when the Judgements of God were upon him, he would promiſe to let them go, but it was upon condition, that they might leave ſome thing behind them, that he might make a prey upon, therefore he bid them go, but leave their flocks and heards behind them, but <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithfull, and ſaid not a hoof ſhould be left behind.</p>
                  <p>And ſo <hi>Iohn Bulkley</hi> and the reſt who ſit in darkneſs and rule with the powers thereof, hath imbondaged the Servants of God, for which his Judgements hath often come near the heart of him, and others, even thick darkneſs which they might feel over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering their hearts, even bringing them down to the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death, and then in their minds, and alſo in words would promiſe to let us go, but it was upon condition, that we ſhould leave ſomething behind us, for he or they to make a prey upon; therefore it was offered we might go if we would leave an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33077:25"/> behind us, by giving ſecurity to go home, and when they could not have that then they would have us leave a promiſe behind us, by promiſing to go home, and when they could not have that, then they would have ſome words to that purpoſe, or ſome deſires from us, for <hi>Iohn Bulkley</hi> asked <hi>Ann Read,</hi> what was deſired, and if any thing was deſired it ſhould be done, but we did not deſire any thing as to beg it of them, but vvait for true juſtice and judgement, and vvhen <hi>Iohn Bulkley</hi> vvith the reſt ſaw that not a hoof nor the leaſt thing ſhould be left behind of ours for him and them to boaſt of afterwards, then he, and more of them were tormented, and refuſed to let us go out of their bondage from under their Oppreſſors, and out of their Work-houſe, like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who alſo kept the Servants of God in his bondage, under his work, therefore was he deſtroyed for ever, as theſe are in danger to be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus much at preſent of the unreaſonableneſs of the Rulers and the bruitiſhneſs of the Prieſts,</hi> Jer. 10. 21. <hi>next may be expected to come forth our cruel ſufferings in the priſon, under</hi> Em. Hobs, <hi>whom it is more fit that ſhe her ſelf were kept in a houſe of correction or in chaines, then to be ſuffered to be a Goaler, who hath alſo ſuffered other Friends to be much abuſed that came to viſit us, who were at firſt like to ſuffer to death in this priſon, and houſe of correction, where the Servant (who is not greater then his Lord) doth ſuffer by them of whom I am called,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Humphry Smith.</signed>
                     <dateline>Finiſhed in <hi>Wincheſter</hi> common Goal, and houſe of correction, <date>the 6. day of the week, the 6. day of the 6, month, 58.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The ſounding voice of the dread of Gods mighty power, to all the Judges and Rulers of the earth, who riſe up againſt the Lamb, And to <hi>Gog, Magog,</hi> and all their Armys, And to the whole hoſt of the powers of darkneſs, and to all men, who fight against God, who, or whatſoever they be (or whatſoever they are called.)</head>
            <p>BEhold ye Rulers of the earth, liſten and heare, all ye earthly minded men, let the blindneſs of you minds be opened, that your dark hearts may be enlightened, hear I ſay and ſtop not your cares, you whoſe minds are in the earth, whoſe eyes are cloſed, whoſe hearts are covered, with a thick vail, by your own iniquity, who ſee not the wonders of the Lord, wrought among the living,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33077:26"/> neither perceive the mighty power of the God of the whole earth; who are beſotted through the ſinfulneſs of your continual tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and are groveling as moles in the earth, &amp; laden with thick clay, and covered with the vail that is ſpread over all fleſh, that you ſee not the glory of the God of life, neither perceive ye the comlineſs, of the holy one of <hi>Jacob,</hi> to whom the bright morning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar, is as a cloud of darkneſs, and the way of the living God, as a fierſe whirlwind of fire, who ſee not him that dwelt in the Buſh, neither hear his voice, who hath made darkneſs his habitation, and his pavilion round about him, thick clouds of the ſky.</p>
            <p>Heare I ſay, and let my words, have entrance in you, and let the ſound of my voice, take place in your hearts, let the opening of my lips give aſtoniſhment to the wicked, and the inlargement of my heart the confounding of the Heathen, let the dread of the Lord take hold upon the Hypocrites, and aſtoniſhment ſeaze upon the double minded, let the prudent keep ſilence and heare, and let the honourable be quiet and conſider, let the underſtanding give au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to my words, and let the mouth of the fool be ſtopt, let the ſinner ſtand ſtill and be quiet, and let the ungodly conſider the words of truth, rebel not againſt the word of the Lord, neither har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den your hearts againſt the dread of his power, let the tall ceders bow and bend, and that which is lifted up be brought down, and ſtand ye all in meekneſs.</p>
            <p>For behold the omnipotent power is come, the rock of ages is revealed, the everlaſting ſtrength is made manifeſt, the God of <hi>Abraham</hi> hath reacht forth his hand, and the Redeemer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is come to dwell in the midſt the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath uttered his voice, and he whoſe Name is <hi>I Am,</hi> is at hand, he that moveth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waters may be felt, &amp; he that formeth the ſeed in the womb may be known, he that inhabiteth eternity, is come to dwell in his people, and walk in the middeſt of the poor deſpiſed of his flock, having cleanſed them by the waſhing of water, and renewed them by the Spirit of burning, &amp; refined them, with his righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and clenſed them with the blood of his Son, that in his <hi>Sion</hi> (redeemed with judgement) he may dwell for ever more, and take up his reſt in the middeſt of his people, having made the place of his feet glorious, and his reſidence as a ſeat in the middeſt of a fire, which fire burneth againſt all them that are in the night, and given light to them that are in the covenant, whoſe glory is hid from the dark mind, and his councel withholden from the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33077:26"/> in heart, he ſtandeth near unto the wicked, who perceiveth him not, and taketh notice of his ſecret intents, he obſerveth the footſteps of the Kings of the earth, and marketh the decrees of the unrighteous, and when they have filled up their meaſure, he putteth forth his finger to their life, and taketh away their breath, he ſuddenly cuts off the wicked, and regardeth not the mightineſs of Princes, he ſearcheth the hearts of the Kings, and ruleth over the powers of men, his infiniteneſs, can never be declared, in his hand is the breath of the life of the ſouls of all man-kind.</p>
            <p>Heare I ſay and conſider my words, and ponder the meditations of my mind, for behold the Lord God of life is come, <hi>Immanuel</hi> is revealed, the Root and offſpring of <hi>David</hi> is grown up as a plant of renown, the Seed of the ſhepherd fits upon the throne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him ſhall all the Kings of the earth lay down their Crowns; every Emperor ſhall bow and bend; and the Potentates of the earth (before him) ſhall wither as a green hearb, their glory ſhall periſh as the untimely birth of the womb, their honour ſhall vainiſh as the ſmoke before the wind; their wiſdom ſhall fade away, as a bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom cut off, and their underſtandings ſhall come to nothing; the wiſdome of the moſt high ſhall be exalted over them all, and with his fooliſhneſs, will he them all confound, yea with a fooliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will he anger the Judges of the earth, and with a deſpiſed people will he provoke the Rulers of the world to jealouſie, by the fooliſhneſs of his flock, will he confound his enemies, and by his weakneſs in them, will he ſubdue the ſtrength of the mighty, and though all his enemies (ſtrive) in the arrogancy of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and in the fierceneſs of their ſtrength, yet ſhall he be exalted, who is lead as a Lamb dumb, and he ſhall reign whoſe right it is, in whoſe mouth there is found no guile, who maketh an end of ſin, and bringeth in everlaſting righteouſneſs, and ſetteth up judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the heart, and cometh to rule in the Kingdomes of men, and overturneth the hoſt of his enemies, by whom Judges are lead away fools, deviners turned made, before whoſe preſence the mightineſs of the mightieſt Rulers of the earth is as wax before the fire, and their ſtrength meltteth away as the fat of Lambs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore hear and ſee, O ye kindreds and Rulers of the earth, the Lord our God is come, the might of his ſtrength is revealed, &amp; the power of his preſence made known; he hath choſen his Army to himſelf, &amp; their names are written in his life; he hath numbred up his hoſts together, and armed his choſen with his everlaſting
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33077:27"/> ſtrength; the Captain of his hoſt goeth before them, and the camp of the Lord is very great, they are numberleſs as the ſand of the Sea, and infinite as the ſtars of heaven: Even ſo is the ſeed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> the remnant of the flock of <hi>Jacob,</hi> whom the Lord hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, who are choſen, and faithful, and true; yea, behold it's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo, and that all the Nations of the earth ſhall know, for the Lord of hoſts rideth on in meekneſs, in the midſt of his hoſt, and maketh War in righteouſneſs, with the enemies of the Lamb, who would not that he ſhould reign, who makes an end of ſin, and he is cloathing his Army with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eal as with a garment, and covering them with the armour of light, and preſerveth their head in the day of battel, and girds them up with ſtrength, and guideth their feet upon the rock, and preſerveth their life under the ſhadow of his hand. When he ſpeaketh the word, his Army goeth forth, and at his command they march on their way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> He liſteth up a Standard before them, and proclaimeth open War againſt the Inhabitants of the Earth, who now hear that the Lamb is come to reign in Righteouſneſs, and to ſtain the pride of their glory, and confound the height of their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and lay their honour in the duſt for ever.</p>
            <p>Therefore all Kindreds of the earth, even <hi>Gog, Magog,</hi> and all the hoſts of the heathen, are riſing up in the bitterneſs of their ſpirits, in the height of the power of the man of ſinne, joyning all their forces together, as in one band of darkneſſe, taking counſell from <hi>Aegypt, making a covenant with death, and an agreement with hell,</hi> and gathering up the utmoſt powers of darkneſs to be as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge unto them: And thus in the ſtrength of the King of the child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of pride, they are riſing up againſt the Lord, even the God of life, and againſt his anointed ones, who have indeed and in truth <hi>received the anointings, and need not man to teach them, but are all taught of the Lord God Almighty, who alſo teacheth their hands to war, and their fingers to fight:</hi> And he utters his voice as the ſound of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters, before his Army, who followeth him in the might of his power, whoſe preſence is dreadful in the midſt of his hoſt, and there is none that is able to ſtand before him, for he is a conſuming fire in the midſt of his Camp, and burneth up his enemies round about; and before him and his Army ſhall all faces gather pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, everlaſting ſhame ſhall cover the glory of all fleſh, before him all people ſhall be much pained, his dread and vengeance ſhall take hold on all his adverſaries; His redeemed ſhall march with him in the travail of their ſouls, from <hi>ſtrength to ſtrength</hi> ſhall they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33077:27"/> on, and none ſhall be feeble among them; their arrows ſhall reach into the bowels of the ſcornful, and their words of life pierce the hearts of the hypocrites. They ſhall tread upon Kings, as upon mortar, and trample upon the wicked as upon aſhes; they fear not the greateſt <hi>Goliah's,</hi> neither yet the wickedneſs of the pride of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> unrighteous Decrees cannot ſtop their mouths, nor the fear of a Furnace, or a Dungeon with-hold them from their way, all fleſh is as graffe before them, and at their rebuke ſhall the potſheards of the earth be broken for ever; before them there is no Nation ſhall ſtand, for one of them ſhall chaſe a hundred, and before five ſhall the ſtrength and wiſdome of a thouſand be confounded.</p>
            <p>And this the Lords Army ſhall never be confounded, and his glory in them ſhall never be defaced, nor his power with them ſhal never be overcome, nor his ſtrength in them ſhall never be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; therefore in vain do all the potſherds of the earth ſtrive; <hi>For they that riſe up against them ſhall be as flax before the fire, and the mightieſt among the ſons of men ſhall be as the graſſe that is cut downe;</hi> for the Lords hoſt is very terrible, and in meekneſs is the Lamb ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on to judgement, his followers are enrobed with the light of the morning, and adorned with the beauty of the Sun. Their eyes are enlightned with the light of the moſt high, &amp; they ſee through the dark parts of all their enemies, and diſcern the ſecret plottings of all their adverſaries. Their wiſdom comes in like a river, and their underſtanding ſhall never be darkned. Their ſtrength is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed as the morning, and they are valiant to do exploits. The wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the wiſe before them ſhall be confounded for ever, and the underſtanding of the prudent be eſteemed as a thing of nought. They ſpy out the lurkings of their enemies, and ſee through the coverings of the deceitful. Of their ſtrength they ſhall never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, neither ſhall their weapons be taken from them. Their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge ſhall never be ſhaken, nor the place of their reſt removed. The wicked ſhall never enter upon their dwellings, nor all their enemies invade the land of their reſt; for the deſire of all Nations to them is come &amp; him that they long waited for have they now received. And they tread upon the Cocka-trice den, and meet the devouring Lyons; in the power of the Fathers love there is no deadly thing that doth them hurt, nor any weapon formed againſt them that ever ſhall proſper.</p>
            <p>And this is <hi>Sion,</hi> the redeemed of the Lord, the glory of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> whom the Lord hath choſen, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33077:28"/> ſet up on high over all the kindreds of the earth, which ſtands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the enemies of the Lord, and is his new threſhing inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with which he will threſh the Heathen in his anger, and bath, his ſword in the blood of the ſlain, for behold his ſword ſhall devour much fleſh, and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many; with <hi>Sion</hi> the perfection of beauty will the Lord break in pieces, wound, confound and overturn for ever, the horſe and his Rider; the Captain and his Troop; the Ancient and honourable; the Prophet that telleth lyes, yea all the hoſt of the unrighteous, and the ſtrength of the Army of the man of ſin, and the beauty of the whore that rides upon the beaſt, and all them who ſet themſelves in battel againſt the Lord, and all them who lead into captivity and would captivate the Servants of the Lamb, ſhall go into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity for ever.</p>
            <p>For behold the Lord is with us, the Shout of a King is among us, the Lord whoſe name is holy is come, he hath uttered his voice from Heaven, and now the Nations of the earth are angry, but the Lord will reign in righteouſneſs, and all his enemies ſhall be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at his preſence, and his adverſaries ſhall be amazed for ever, their hearts ſhall be turned as a ſtone within them, and men ſhall be at their wits end, for fear and for looking after thoſe things which ſhall come upon the earth, and all them whoſe names are written in it, their wiſdome ſhall not preſerve them, their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings ſhall not defend them, neither ſhall all their ſubtilty co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them from the Light, their nakedneſs ſhall appear to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting ſhame, and the priſoners of hope ſhall rejoyce over them for ever more.</p>
            <p>For behold I ſay your day is come, wherein you ſhall bow down under the priſoners, and fall under the ſlain, according to the words of the ſpirit of prophecy, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 10. 4. and the ſlain over you ſhall rejoyce for ever more, having the high prayſes of God in their mouths, and the ſword of the ſpirit in their hearts, with which they ſhall cut in pieces and pierce in ſunder, the bowels of all fleſh, and it ſhall be as chaff before them, and the ſtrength there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as the paſſing away of the morning cloud, and in the ſtrength of the moſt high, ſhall the Army of the <hi>Lyon of the tribe of Judah,</hi> go on and proſper, even as <hi>Kings,</hi> whoſe Armies are ſwift to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, their faces are as an Adamant, and their countenances fierce, and terrible, the ſound of their voice is dreadful, and the noiſe of their appearance aſtoniſheth the Heathen, the earth before them is full
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33077:28"/> of its fruit, behind them its a deſolate wilderneſs, they ſpare not the ancient, nor the honourable, neither have they reſpect to the perſons of men; they even ſmile at deſtruction when it's coming, and they are prepared for all your oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>Wherefore now gather your ſelves together, O ye potſheards of the earth, and ſtand up all you that thirſt for blood, aſſemble your ſelves together all ye perſecutors, let your counſels come up from hell, and let the depth of the powers of darkneſs ſhew forth it ſelfe in the utmoſt of its ſtrength, and with it combine ye all together, and ſtand up in the power of your King, which is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the <hi>bottomleſs pit,</hi> who is head among (in) and over all you who thirſteth for the blood of the innocent. Now come and draw near in the very height of your Fathers wrath, and behold we meet you in the infiniteneſs of our Fathers love, and ſtand you together in the depth of your ſecret ſubtilty, and behold we abide in the pure wiſdome of the moſt High. Stand ye up for the glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the world, and we abide faithful for the glory of the Lord our maker.</p>
            <p>And this I ſay plainly unto you, that your long tyranny will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver weary but the patience we have received, neither can you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict more puniſhment then the Lord hath enabled us to bear; and as your wrath is increaſed, our humility is increaſed much more; and as you are filled, and moved with envy, we are much more fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and overcome with the power of the Fathers life; and though you contrive wayes to enſnare the innocent, we take no thought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand to deliver our ſelves, for ſelfe we have denyed, and we have given up our bodies and ſouls a living ſacrifice unto God, to do or ſuffer his will. And him that kills the body we feare not, much leſſe thoſe that can but whip or impriſon but for a few moneths; for our life you cannot reach, neither can you diſturb their reſt whom the Lord hath crowned with honour, who out of the world are redeemed and bought with the price of blood moſt precious, but are become his, to follow him whither ever he lead them, though it be through tryals, great tribulations, bonds and long impriſonments, theſe things cannot move them who are brought to reſt in the deſerts, and ſleep in the woods; Yea, and there is none can make them afraid with all their threats, unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Laws, bonds, Bridewels, long unjuſt impriſonments, or death it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33077:29"/>
            <p>And this honour hath the Saints, and herein do they rejoyce for evermore, in that they are counted worthy to ſuffer for his Names ſake, who was made perfect through ſufferings, and thereby over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all the powers of Darkneſſe, whereby <hi>Principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are ſpoiled for ever, and through ſufferings are we made more then conquerours over all our enemies,</hi> whoſe day will have an end, whoſe cruelty will ceaſe, whoſe tyranny will be rewarded upon their own heads, and their memoriall will rot for ever; but the faithfulneſſe of the faithfull ſhall never be taken from him, nor the innocency of the harmleſſe ſhall never be forgotten, neither ſhall they ever want ſtrength to ſtand in the day of battell, nor courage and boldneſſe to endure, when the enemies of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth up in oppoſition againſt the brightneſſe of the riſing of the power of the Lamb of God, who is come to take away the ſin of the world, even him who is the Light, and the Heir, againſt whom with one conſent, the Rulers of the earth, the Hireling Prieſts, with all the prophane, and unclean, and all them of all opinions in the world, are joyning together in one combination, as with oneminde conſpiring in their enmity, to ſlay, and murther the Heir that is now come to make an end of ſin, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33077:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
